<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Mercury-gallant containing many true and pleasant relations of what hath passed at Paris, from the first of January 1672. Till the Kings departure thence. Translated from the French.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212976</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896335</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896335</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154286</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89081)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154286)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2409:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Mercury-gallant containing many true and pleasant relations of what hath passed at Paris, from the first of January 1672. Till the Kings departure thence. Translated from the French.</title>
                  <author>J. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 159, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.R. and N.T. for Dorman Newman at the Kings Arms in the Poultry, and Jonathan Edwin at the Three Roses in Ludgate-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: J.D.</note>
                  <note>French original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Social life and customs --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154286:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154286:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154286:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154286:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Mercury-Gallant: Containing Many True and Pleaſant RELATIONS Of what hath paſſed at PARIS, From the Firſt of <hi>January</hi> 1672. Till the KINGS Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated from the French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and <hi>N. T.</hi> for <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the Kings Arms in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> and <hi>Jonathan Edwin</hi> at the Three Roſes in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:154286:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154286:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>To my much honoured Friend, George Bowerman Eſquire.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome men (not ſo good as you) might perhaps think that while I have thus long been unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately hindred from paying the reſpects due to your many good Offices and Kindneſſes, I have blotted them quite out of my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory,
<pb facs="tcp:154286:4"/>and become utterly unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving both of them, or any fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Favour; and there may poſſibly ſome Reaſons be urged for the entertainment of ſuch ſuſpicions: but I am more than half confident they cannot at all have reached you: for as your Kindneſſes were free and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtrained, out of your own pure and natural Goodneſs, ſo <hi>I</hi> am bound to believe they were accompanied with a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which cannot eaſily think it ſelf deceived, becauſe it were both a ſin and ſhame it ſhould be.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:154286:4"/>
            <p>And therefore to endeavour the beſt I can to diſperſe any ſuch Clouds that may be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I have taken this courſe to let you perceive that I have preſerved a Remembrance of You and your Kindneſſes, and am meditating of them, even when you perhaps may believe they are leaſt in my Thoughts; and though this be the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt way in the World to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite Courteſies, and can no way form an Aquittance for any Obligation, yet at worſt 'tis an Acknowledgment, which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous
<pb facs="tcp:154286:5"/>Minds uſe to receive in good part, and where they find it, think the Defection of a Larger Satisfaction, proceeds rather from Misfortune than Fault.</p>
            <p>As ſuch then, Pleaſe to accept this ſmall Preſent I now ſend you, which when in the Original, was thought worthy of being preſented unto the <hi>FRENCH KING:</hi> and was a Book He Himſelf paſſed the Licenſe for under His Seal, when He officiated
<pb facs="tcp:154286:5"/>as His own CHANCEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R.</p>
            <p>I will not prevent You with its Contents: Let them ſpeak for themſelves. Onely thus much I will ſay, That in my Judgment it may be as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſeful for This Horizon as That for which it was Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated. And if the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Stories contained in it, ſhall give You and other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen that ſhall peruſe it, any Divertiſement, I ſhall have received my Satisfaction,
<pb facs="tcp:154286:6"/>and have no more to addle, but to beg you to value me ſtill, as one that will ever be,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed> Your moſt faithful and moſt humble Servant, <hi>J. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:154286:6"/>
            <head>THE <hi>French Bookseller</hi> TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Believe now I have hit on a Book will pleaſe all the world, becauſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of matter it contains. Thoſe who are wholly addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb facs="tcp:154286:7"/>to Romantick writings, will here find Stories, though true, yet as pleaſing and diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſant, as in any of the moſt exquiſite Books of that Kind; the curious, and the Countrey Gentleman, and the Stranger, who never had the leaſt knowledge of many perſons of high birth, and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary worth, will in this Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, and thoſe ſhall follow it, find the ſprings of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown, and what has made them eſteemable. To know the value of any perſon you ſhall only need to turn over
<pb facs="tcp:154286:7"/>the <hi>Mercury-Gallant,</hi> and find your wiſh. Every Six months ſhall come forth a Volume, and in the ſecond ſhall be ſet down the expreſs time of their coming out, that people may know when to expect them; and hereafter we ſhall take the liberty to ſpeak of Forreign Courts and Countries. The Author begins now to ſettle his correſpondencies, and to ſearch out the ways of the moſt conſiderable aſſiſtances, that nothing of Novelty may happen in the world, which his Letters ſhall not ſpeak of.
<pb facs="tcp:154286:8"/>Theſe are but Eſſayes; but by what they are, you may judge what will follow: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider therefore this only as the deſign of a work which time will better poliſh. Thoſe who know any thing of Gallantry, or worthy to be made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, may bring it to me, who will engage the Author to entertain with it the perſon to whom he addreſſes his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. I think my ſelf likewiſe obliged to give notice, that this Book has no reſemblance with the <hi>Journal des ſcavans;</hi> that treats only of ſuch Books
<pb facs="tcp:154286:8"/>of Sciences as are publiſhed, and this of pretty Love-ſtories and intrigues, and of the worth of perſons any way extraordinary, though their Pens never made them fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous. It is not of neceſſity that all who have wit muſt be writers, there are many proofs to the contrary, and I will add, that if here any Books be ſpoke of, they are only Books of Gallantry, and of which the <hi>Journal</hi> ſayes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and that there is not in the whole Treatiſe twenty lines to that purpoſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:154286:9"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 21. l. 19. dele ſo. p. 22. l. 10. for with r. the. p. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. l. 7. for woman r. women. p. p. 33. l. 19. for foryed r. forced. p. 44. l: 1. for Balads r. Ballets. p. 51. l. 14. dele and. p. 63. l. 11. for ſeventy r. ſeverity. l. 19. for. her r. his. p. 71. l. 3. for any r. an. p. 72. l. 12. for ſweezing r. ſqueezing. l. 13. for his r. her. p: 73. l. 15. for unmatched r. unmasked. p. 74. l. 2. after theſe r. perſwaſions. l. 11. dele or l. p: 81. l. 16. for it r. its p. 63. l. 18. for Faries r. Farces. p. 98. l. 14. for Jeſtu r. Teſtu.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:154286:9"/>
            <head>THE TABLE OF Matters contained in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter I.</label> THe Deſign of the Work. The Story of the Neclace of Pearl. Honours paid to the memory of the late Madam <hi>de Montauſier.</hi> The eſtabliſhment of the Academy of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecture, of which the <hi>Sieur Blon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> is to be Profeſſor.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter II.</label> The Story of the Green Silk Stockings. The reception of the Duke
<pb facs="tcp:154286:10"/>
                  <hi>de Feuillade</hi> to the charge of Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of the <hi>French</hi> Regiment of Guards. Elogy of the Marſhal <hi>du Pleſſis.</hi> Diſcourſe on <hi>Bajazet</hi> a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy of the <hi>Sieur Racines.</hi> Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures happened to a <hi>French</hi> man at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> by which <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Gallantry may be judged of.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter III.</label> The Story of a Lady, choſe rather to burn with her Husband, then ſee him diſloyal. A Diſcourſe on the Marriage of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> an Heroick Comedy, The arrival of <hi>Monſieur Courtine</hi> in <hi>Sweden.</hi> The depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Duke <hi>d'Eſtrees,</hi> extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Ambaſsador at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter IV.</label> The Hiſtory of the Family of hope. The publick entrance of the <hi>Marquis de Villars</hi> into <hi>Madrid. Monſieur de Pompone's</hi> return from <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:154286:10"/>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter V.</label> The Story of the maiden Souldier Elogy of the Duke of <hi>Coaſlin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter VI.</label> The Death of the Chancellor, and his Elogy. Praiſe of the <hi>Marquis</hi> of <hi>Louvoy.</hi> Death of the Princeſs of <hi>Conty.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter VII.</label> The Elogy of ſix Coanſellors of Eſtate, and ſix maſters of Request, choſen by the King to be Aſſiſtants to the Seal. An accident happened to a young Marchioneſs on the death of <hi>Monſieur Gualtier,</hi> the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent maſter of the Lute.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter VIII.</label> The Story of a man, who would believe he had made himſelf a Cuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kold. <hi>Monſieur de Pachau's</hi> worth acknowledged by the King. <hi>Meffieurs de Vendoſme</hi> their return from
<pb facs="tcp:154286:11"/>
                  <hi>Italy.</hi> The Kings choiſe of <hi>Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur de Camus</hi> for firſt Preſident of the Court of Aids.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter IX.</label> The death of <hi>Monſieur Deſpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha</hi> Marquis <hi>de Ternes.</hi> The Reception of the Cavalier <hi>d'Arquien</hi> into his fathers Charge.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter X.</label> The death of Monſieur <hi>de la Motte Houdancourt.</hi> The promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tton of Monſieur the Arch Biſhop of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> to the Cardinalate. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe on <hi>Ariana.</hi> a Tradegy of the younger <hi>Corneilles.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter XI.</label> The Story of the Cloſet of Looking-glaſses. Diſcourſe on a Comedy of <hi>Molieres,</hi> called <hi>les Femmes ſcavantes,</hi> or the wiſe Women.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter XII.</label> The occaſien of the <hi>French</hi> Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demies
<pb facs="tcp:154286:11"/>Voyage to <hi>Verſailles,</hi> under the Conduct of the Arch Biſhop of <hi>Paris.</hi> Monſieur the Marquis <hi>de Angeau</hi> his treating the Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter XIII.</label> The Eſtabliſhment of all the King of <hi>France</hi> his Forces, as well Horſe as Foot, with the Names of all the Regiments, the Companies they contain, and the number of their Men.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter XIV.</label> Diſcourſe of the Waters, Gardens, and new imbeliſhments of <hi>Verſailles,</hi> with the Names of the Statua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter XV.</label> The Praiſes of Cardinal <hi>de Retz.</hi> The Eſtates of <hi>Brittain</hi> preſented by <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Duke of <hi>Chaune.</hi> the Duke of <hi>Bethune</hi> mode Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant
<pb facs="tcp:154286:12"/>General of <hi>Picardy,</hi> and the Duke <hi>de Duras</hi> Captain of the <hi>Gardes du Corps.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter XVI.</label> The Inſtitution of the Academy <hi>Des belles Lettres,</hi> with the names of the Academians. An account of the Iugenuity of <hi>Gas,</hi> Madam the Marquis of <hi>Deſhoulieres</hi> Spaniel. The Death of <hi>Monſieur de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangis.</hi> Praiſes of the Baron of <hi>Schonborn,</hi> Nephew to the Elector of <hi>Magence,</hi> and bis extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Envoy. The Entrance and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of <hi>Conde de Molina</hi> extraordinary Ambaſſador from <hi>Spain,</hi> with Obſervations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter XVII.</label> An account of the new Modes, as well for Men and Women, as for the furniture of the houſe. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
<pb facs="tcp:154286:12"/>of the primier Preſidents Son, to <hi>Madamoiſelle Chaluces.</hi> The Kings choiſe of Phyſitians, Diſcourſe on the <hi>Journal des ſcavans.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter XVIII.</label> The Names of the General Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Army. The Names of the Ships, and Commanders of the <hi>French</hi> Kings Navy Royal.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Letter XIX.</label> Diſcourſe on ſeveral Books of Gallantry. The Namcs of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors quoted by <hi>Monſieur Menage</hi> in his Book intituled. <hi>Obſervations on the</hi> French <hi>Tongue.</hi> The Speech of the Colledge of Phyſitians to the three principal Phyſitians. Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Kings giving the Seals to Monſieur <hi>d'Aligre.</hi> The departure of the Baggages of the Army. Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe on the preparation of a <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoleum,</hi> of which Monſieur <hi>de Bru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <pb facs="tcp:154286:13"/>is the deſigner. The Audience of the ſeveral Ambaſſadors and Reſidents of the King; as alſo of the Sovereign Courts and Provoſt of Merchants. The Kings departure, ſome words much in Mode; the ſtory of <hi>Megius,</hi> and his Companion, or the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers Stone.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154286:13"/>
            <head>THE MERCURY GALLANT.</head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>Letter I.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Needed not have been put in mind of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe I made you at your going from <hi>Paris,</hi> to ſend you often an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſuch Novelties as were worthy of the curioſity of the moſt ingenious perſons of that Countrey, which is like for ſo long a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154286:14"/>time to be made happy with your reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. They which have the perſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in their thoughts, ſeldom forget their promiſes. I doubt not Madam, but you underſtand ſo well what that means, that I need explain it no further. Proceed we therefore to our News, or rather firſt, to the order I have reſolved to obſerve in giving you theſe accounts. I will pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually write to you once in eight days, and then give you the moſt particular and curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous relation I can of all that has happened in the week aforegoing. Sending you things, which the Gazets give no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of, or at leaſt not ſo full and clear a one. The moſt minute things that paſs here ſhall not eſcape my Quill: You ſhall have all Deaths and Weddings of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, with ſuch Circumſtances as may create that delight in ſuch news, which they have not in themſelves. I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to unravel the truth of all great actions, where valour ſhall make it ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in the Army, and will often lay naked before you things which fame gives but at random; becauſe ſhe not ſtaying to ſearch the depth of them, the firſt rumours
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154286:14"/>ſhe ſpreads are for the moſt part ſhort of truth. I will not forget to tell you who receive favours from our great Monarch; he gives with ſo endearing a grace, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough his gifts are always conſiderable, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he obliging manner with which he gives, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reeds often as much delight in the hearer; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the magnificence of his gifts in the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er; and whereas there often happens pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eedings ſo extraordinary, and ſo full of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntrigue, that the beſt invented Romances <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome ſhort of them, I ſhall nor fail to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ertiſe you with them, and ſend you the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eal Circumſtances, which are ſeldom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nown but to perſons who make diligent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arch after them. Curioſity bringing to <hi>Paris</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot only many brave people from all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inces of <hi>France,</hi> but likewiſe numbers of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rangers. I will give you advice of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orth of thoſe attract any admiration. I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill ſend you all ſuch witty pieces as have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y reputation, as Songs, Verſes, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er ſuch like works. I will ſend you the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cceſs of all new Plays, and what Books <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gallantry are Printed: I ſay of Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y, becauſe I pretend not to ſpeak of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oſe which concern Arts or Sciences,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154286:15"/>not being able to perform it ſo well as thoſe who every fifteen days give us an account of them. But I will do ſomewhat more then I have yet promiſed, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſend you ſome new adventures in form of Hiſtories. <hi>Paris</hi> is big enough to furniſh me with them, and every day ſomething conſiderable happens there, and thoſe who make it part of their buſineſs to underſtand the Town often hear of ſtrange adventures, and are ſometimes witneſs to them: ſo that I fear not the giving you a new Story almoſt every week; and when <hi>Paris</hi> fails by chance to furniſh me, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doubt to learn ſomewhat divertſiing from the great number of ſtrangers are continually in this City I will add to this all the News worth hearing from the <hi>Ruelle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Balls, or any meetings, and here with not omit the new Modes, the Countrey is generally well pleaſed to know them, nor can I readily t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll any thing they more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; I believe likewiſe you will be of my mind, that the Miſſes of <hi>Paris</hi> will often furniſh me with pleaſant ſubjects, and that all theſe things together and apart, will continually ſupply me with a ſack full of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154286:15"/>news, wherewithall to entertain you: I ſhall yet meddle little with forreign news, or matters of State, and ſpeak only of thoſe great publick news of which people diſcourſe every where, who make no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of underſtanding them; but as there is no news ſo publick, but has ſomething of privacy in it; I will ſend you the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of thoſe who ſhould know things beſt. If I proſecute my deſign, and you keep my Letters, they may for the future ſerve as Memories to the curious, and many things may be met with here, cannot be found elſewhere, becauſe of the diverſity of the matter; but it matters not much whether they be uſeful to others, ſo they divertiſe you; that's my only aim and therefore I begin with a pleaſant Story before I enter upon the particularities of this weeks news.</p>
               <p>A young gallant coming ſome days ſince to viſit a fair Lady, to whom he had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pretence of love, then to keep him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf it talk (for 'tis a moſt ordinary pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice here, and the moſt part of our young people, if they be put out of the road of talking a little love to the Ladies, and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154286:16"/>their beauties, have not a word to ſay for themſelves) This young blade, who I am telling this ſtory of, having run over, and over all the Leſſons he had learnt, in praiſing every particular charm of the beauty he came to wait on, and at laſt quite ſtranded himſelf, not knowing any other way to entertain her; this lovely perſon tyred with hearing the ſame things again and again, firſt ſlumbred a little, and at laſt fell faſt aſleep, though ſhe deſigned it not; but having wearied her ſelf the night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at a Ball, and reliſhing ſo ill now the tedious divertiſement of him that entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her, ſleep ſeized her unawares. The Gallant had a fate quite contrary; the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this fair ſleeper, and the motion of her Breaſts as ſhe breathed, awakened his Senſes; he viewed her with a great deal of paſſion, and his heart oft told him, he ought to improve the opportunity; but whilſt he ſtood gazing, and not knowing what to reſolve, he caſt his Eyes on a Neck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of Pearl, worth twenty thouſand Livers, which ſhe had about her Neck, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, That the Ribbon which tyed it, did as it were preſent it ſelf to him. This idle
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154286:16"/>lover, whoſe name I will conceal under that of <hi>Cleontes,</hi> was immediately ſurprized with imaginations quite contrary to thoſe he had had but a minute before. He had about two dayes ſince loſt all his Money at play, he was naturally expenſive, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready owed ſo much, that his credit was almoſt crackt; beſides, he was young, and had always been a little inclinable to knavery, and all theſe incouragements meeting together, ſoon formed in him a temptation, utterly different from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and now all his amorous glances were caſt at the Neck-lace. After having a good while viewed it, he turned his eyes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the door, his thoughts began all at once to run one way, but yet he could not fix them; he gets up, walks two or three turns about the Chamber, comes to the Stairs head to ſee if any body might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance be coming; but finding all things favouring his deſign, returns to <hi>Beliſa;</hi> (for ſo I ſhall call this fair Lady in the ſequel of the ſtory.) He was no ſooner come nigh her, but he grew as ſtiff as a ſtatue, and ſtood like one that had loſt all ſenſe and motion, making reflexions on the action he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154286:17"/>was about. I am here alone ſaid he to himſelf, and none elſe can be charged with the Neck-lace but my ſelf, and if I go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way without ſaying any thing, I conclude my ſelf guilty. If I ſtay after I have taken it, they will make ſuch ſtrict ſearch, that they will find it about me, hide it where I can: I had much better let it alone, and relinquiſh ſo vile an attempt. But if I let it alone (replyed he ſuddenly to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) can I ever in reaſon hope fortune ſhould again do any thing for me, and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thouſand Franks will be a very conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſum for me, he then began to caſt up in his head how he would diſpoſe thoſe twenty thouſand Livers. He would pay but few debts, but inſtead of that he would put himſelf into a magnificent Equipage, as to Cloaths, buy ſuch and ſuch Points and Laces, and put his Train into the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Liveries in the World, and with ſuch a tempting adjuſtment, he though himſelf ſecure of the Conqueſt of at leaſt a dozen hearts of thoſe gay women, who are taken with fine out-ſides, and are ſooner ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with gaudery then worth, who are ſo ſottiſh to think he cannot be a worthy man,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154286:17"/>who has not brisk accouterments, or keeps but a modeſt train. <hi>Cleontes</hi> having thus diſpoſed the twenty thouſand Livers in his Coxcombe, takes the Neck-lace; but he was no ſooner maſter of it, then he felt a trembling over all his body, and ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with a violent fear of being ſurprized with it about him he reſolved to return it: He was juſt about executing what his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret repentance had determined, when it came into his head to ſwallow the Neck-lace, which conſiſted of two and thirty Pearls. 'Twas a hard task this, but his greedy deſire of ſo much money brought it to effect. When he had ſwallowed the laſt Pearl, he began to be as much troubled what to do with the Ribbon; he was a good while ſtudying how to diſpoſe it, and at length concluded to cut it into ſuch little ſcraps as were ſcarce perceptible. You muſt think he was a good while doing all this, and therefore may the eaſier believe <hi>Beliſa</hi> awakened almoſt as ſoon as he had done, ſhe asks preſently for her Neck-lace. <hi>Cleontes</hi> denyes the having taken it, ſhe thought he only intended to make her ſearch for it, and very gallantly turns all into 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154286:18"/>a Jeſt, but was ſtrangely troubled when ſhe perceived he ſtill denyed it, will all that ſeriouſneſs men uſe when they would have what they ſay thought truth. If you will <hi>(ſaid he to her)</hi> command another ſuit of Cloaths to be given me, I will ſtrip my ſelf before any body you ſhall name, and leave mine with you; nay, they ſhall have my very Shirt to ſearch. <hi>Beliſa</hi> was in more then a peck of troubles. Certain ſhe was, ſhe had the Neck-lace on before ſhe fell aſleep, and none but <hi>Cleontes</hi> had been in the Chamber, and yet the Neck-lace was not to be found, though ſhe had made as diligent a ſearch, as ſhe could, and a ſearch ſuitable to the greatneſs of her loſs. <hi>Cleantes</hi> urged her to ſearch his Pockets; ſhe believed ſince he preſſed it ſo much, ſhe might chance find it there, and that he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly jeſted all this while to vex her a little, ſhe reſolves therefore to ſatisfy him, with hopes to ſatisfy her ſelf; but juſt as ſhe had put in her hand, <hi>Clidamant</hi> enters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Room, and thinks ſhe was imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him. This <hi>Clidamant</hi> was one of thoſe priviledged lovers, who may come in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knocking, or ſending word who they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154286:18"/>are. 'Twill be an eaſie matter Madam for you to believe, he did or ſaid ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that jealous lovers uſe to do, when they think they find Miſtreſſes falſe, he could not reſtrain himſelf, and <hi>Cleontes</hi> ſeemed to rejoyce rather then be troubled at it, he had hopes this new alarme, might ſuppreſs all farther clamour about the Neck-lace, and having ſome bravery (for heart none can think he wanted, after a Cordial of two and thirty ſuch Pills as he had ſwallowed) he told <hi>Clidamant</hi> he would go forth, and there expect him to decide their difference. The jealous man was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to follow him, when <hi>Beliſa</hi> ſtop'd them both, and told the whole adventure. <hi>Clida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi> thought it ſo ſtrange, that he could not at firſt believe it; but his jealouſy made him determine to try all ways imaginable, to diſcover whether <hi>Beliſa</hi> had told him truth. He was ſtudying how to effect it, when three or four of the afflicted Ladies friends, and of <hi>Clidamants</hi> acquaintance, came into the Room; they ſoon were told how the whole caſe ſtood. Their amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was great, but it was yet made grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when they ſaw nothing could perſwade
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154286:19"/>
                  <hi>Cleontes</hi> to tell what was become of the Neck-lace. Intreaties and threatnings were both imployed, but all to no purpoſe, and the afternoon was quite ſpent without making any diſcovery. <hi>Beliſas</hi> grief for the loſs of her Neck-lace increaſed more and more, as her hopes of ever finding it decayed, ſhe being aſſured, that <hi>Cleontes</hi> muſt have ſtole it, and hid it where ever it was, having either caſt it into ſome by Corner, or thrown it to ſome body out of the Window. The manner in which <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſa</hi> ſpoke this, made all the Gentlemen believe it to be true, and therefore they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to put it to the utmoſt teſt, and as ſoon as it was quite dark they ſent for a Sack which was no ſooner got, but ſeizing all four on <hi>Cleontes,</hi> they violently thruſt him into it, and having tyed it faſt, carryed him to the Window. That Window was two Stories high, and anſwered to a Court, in which lay ſome ſquare ſtones for build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. As ſoon as they had him at the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow they threatned to throw him down; if he would not confeſs what he had done with the Neck-lace, and at laſt ſo terribly frightned him, that he owned he had it,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154286:19"/>promiſed to reſtore it; but deſired time, 'twas granted him, but on condition he ſhould tell what he had done with it, he ſtumbled at that a great while; but finding himſelf preſſed too hard, at length confeſſed the whole truth. Whereupon they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently took him out of the Sack, ſtript him in ſpite of his teeth, and laid him in a ſumptuous bed. And immediately one of the Gentlemen went, and fetch'd a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, which he took care ſhould be ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and by its operation you'l believe it was ſo, <hi>Cleontes</hi> refuſed a great while to take it, but at laſt out of the fear of the ſcandal, he ſubmitted; for they threatned if he did not, to carry him to Priſon, and to publiſh every where that he was a Thief, he had many doleful reachings and ſtrainings, and ſuffered infinite pangs and gripings; but at laſt (though at ſeveral times) he brought up one and thirty of the Pearls: There was one yet behind; he offered to pay double the value for it, but <hi>Clidamont</hi> would have him take the other Potion, which put him to mighty torment before he could bring up the two and thirtieth Pearl, however at length it came, and they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154286:20"/>diſmiſſed the poor unfortunate wretch, who went away purged to the life, and more caſt down then he could have been after ſix months ſickneſs. This Madam, is an adventure happened ſome dayes ſince, and is yet known to few, there is ſomething me thinks ſo new in it, that I dare believe you have ſcarce read the like; but let us proceed to more publick news.</p>
               <p>Though I have no intention at other times to entertain you with the Funeral ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours paid to thoſe, who are of birth emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent enough to be ſpoke of it the Gazet, and that I deſign not to trouble you with reading of publick News, unleſs they be extraordinary; yet I will not omit obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what there is of novelty, in thoſe affairs, which elſe ſeem fitting to be paſſed over in ſilence, becauſe of the little plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure taken in reading them. I believe the news of the ſervice performed at <hi>Roûen</hi> for the late <hi>Madam de Montauſier</hi> is of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and that it being ſo eaſily to be gueſt at, (it being ſo cuſtomary a thing to pay Funeral Rites to the dead) I might, and ought to have let it paſs; and yet the extraordinary worth of this Honourable defunct, and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154286:20"/>particular eſteem <hi>Monſieur Pilot primier</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the Parliament of <hi>Roûen</hi> had for her, occaſioned theſe ſad duties to be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated with ſome Circumſtances worthy remark, and though that honourable and renowned body never uſed to accompany dead Corps, on the like Ceremony; they would needs condeſcend to do ſomewhat extraordinary to honour the memory of a perſon ſo eſteemable for her worth and pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as the late <hi>Madam de Montauſier.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know not whether it be in my Rule to tell you, that the Abbot of <hi>Novalles</hi> hath lately made appear his great wit and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> even to the aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the old Doctors; you will ſay perhaps reading this news, That if I give you an account of all that maintain a <hi>Theſis,</hi> I ſhall ſtuff my Letters with things not at all curious; but when you ſhall underſtand, that he did in his firſt act on matters of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, what others do not till their laſt, you may perhaps think this Circumſtance makes the news worth ſending, and it may induce you to conceive a fancy for this worthy Abbot, which may make you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh him from others, when you hear
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154286:21"/>him ſpoke of; for ſince it is one of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns in writing you News, to give you a knowledge of the deſerts of the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable perſons in <hi>France;</hi> I will let ſlip no occaſion of ſpeaking of them, and if the News I may ſometimes ſend you of them, have nothing weighty enough in it ſelf, to make you underſtand their particular va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue; yet the Elogies I ſhall give them will at leaſt make you know them: And thus the leaſt curious News may be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
               <p>The King continuing dayly to do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing conſiderable for the glory of <hi>France,</hi> has cauſed to be opened here ſome dayes paſt an Academy of Architecture eſtabliſhed by his Majeſty, and <hi>Sieur Blondel,</hi> the Kings Profeſſor in the Mathematicks, and who is likewiſe to officiate in the ſame function, in this gave great Teſtimonies of his wit and judgment in an Oration he made in praiſe of the King on this occaſion. I know not Madam whether you are acquainted with this eminent perſon; but he paſſes in the judgment of moſt men, for a very able man, he has travelled much, ſeen both the <hi>Indies;</hi> had many different imployments, all which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154286:21"/>he has diſcharged with Honour, has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Ships, and 'tis to him that <hi>Paris</hi> is obliged for the deſign of the Courſe, at which he continually labours, and which will beautifie the City from <hi>Port Richlein</hi> to <hi>Port. St. Anthony.</hi> This Madam is all the news I can give you this week, I hope within eight days to ſend you ſomething more divertizing, and entertain you about a Piece ready for the Theatre, which friends to the Author mightily cry up. It has not yet been acted, but without doubt they have reaſon for wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t they ſay, and the ſucceſs will be anſwerable to their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Jan.</hi> 1. 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:154286:22"/>
               <head>Letter II.</head>
               <p>SInce I have propoſed to begin the week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly news, I have tyed my ſelf to write as often as I can, with fome extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry adventure; you have here Madam a true one, which will doubtleſs pleaſe you.</p>
               <p>A young Sovereign Gallant, and amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, being one day walking without the ordinary confident of his Gallanteries, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having ſtudied upon ſomething for a while, haſtily asks for him, which obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged all that Princes Courtiers to look out every was for <hi>Cleodates.</hi> (ſo will I name that favourite, or rather under that name ſpeak of him in the Story, ſince you have given me an <hi>Item,</hi> that I ſhould put feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed names to all the Gallant Adventures, I ſhall get to ſend you) <hi>Philemon,</hi> a young Cavalier, more ſolicitous then any of the reſt, to make his Complements to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite, was moſthappy, and thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the more ſo; becauſe as he imagined his maſter had particularly addreſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154286:22"/>to him to ſeek him; he flyes to <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> houſe, which had a back door dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly opening toward the Princes Palace, and which he found only put to, he muſt have gone a great way about to the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Gate of entrance, and there to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe asked for <hi>Cleodates:</hi> For that Cavalier no leſs Gallant then his Maſter, whoſe Confident he was, had gone out alone, and taking a turn about, came in again by that private door, without being perceived by any of his people. This way then <hi>Philemon</hi> went in without meeting any body; he goes up a little pair of Stairs which ſtood in a by Corner; but which he knew very well, this not being the firſt time he had tryed that paſſage, and came preſently to the Chamber, where he thought he might find <hi>Cleodates;</hi> but ſeeing no one there, he was forced to knock at a little Cloſet door ſtood by it. After having knockt a good while, it came into his head to look through the Key-hole; for he thought he heard ſome body within, he preſently obſerved <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> kiſſing a Lady, but could not diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver who ſhe was, her face being hid from him; only he took notice ſhe had Green
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154286:23"/>Silk Stockings on, and very rich Garters He eaſily gueſſed by their not anſwering nor ſtirring up and down, that they would not have it known they were in that Cloſet and that they would not open the doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for any one whatever. <hi>Philemon</hi> hereupo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> returns with intention to tell the Prince h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> could not find <hi>Cleodates;</hi> he did ſo indeed but 'twas in a way made him ſuſpect there was a myſtery in it; for he could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear laughing at uttering his name. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prince would needs know the reaſon, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very earneſtly required it, he was ſoon ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſatisfied for Sovereigns not being to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed any thing; <hi>Philemon</hi> told him all h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had ſeen. This adventure which one would have thought ſhould have diverted the Prince, begot a dumps in him, made <hi>Philemon</hi> a hundred times repent his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in diſcovering a thing he obſerved grieved his Maſter, and might be prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to <hi>Cleodates.</hi> This Prince loved a young beauty in his Court, and now grew ſuſpicious his favourite might be his Rival; he asked <hi>Philemon</hi> if he knew the Lady he had ſeen by her Legs; <hi>Philemon</hi> was ſo ready to anſwer yes, that he had not time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154286:23"/>how he might by it both diſpleaſe his Maſter, and looſe his Friend. The Prince replyed, If that Lady were one of the Court he would know her e're it were long, and at that inſtant obliged the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs his Wife to ſend for all the Ladies of the Court; and as ſoon as they were come, propoſed to them to mount immediately on horſe-back, and ſee a chaſe; ſome ſaid they ſhould have time given them to put ſhorter Coats, others were of a contrary opinion, The Prince could have wiſhed it, that he might the better have ſeen their Stockings; but then he doubted they might in changing Cloaths, change Stockings too; but whatever he feared, he was ſoon recovered of it, as you will hear by the ſequel. This Prince, who was natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Gallant, appeared ſo in this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſomewhat more ſo then uſual, and talking pleaſantly with all the Ladies, told them, that he would ſet them all on Horſe-back; you may eaſily gueſs what he meant by it, and that by this contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance he only deſigned to diſcover the Lady with the Green Stockings. He had already ſeated a great many, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154286:24"/>finding what he feared to find, when at laſt he diſcovered one of the delicateſt Legs in the world, and on it a Green Silk Stocking. You will be as much ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed as he was Madam, when you ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that it was upon his Miſtreſs he found them; but 'tis no time to ſtand won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering now, or if you will wonder what you have yet to hear, will but amaze you will more. The Prince in deſpair, ſtretcht on the extreams of love and jealouſy, gave a ſhreck at the ſight of thoſe Stockings, and ſtood like one aſtoniſhed; <hi>Philemon,</hi> who was ſtill near him, perceiving the cauſe of his diſquiet, told him in his ear, That the Stockings he had ſeen were of a deeper Green, and the Garters of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Colour. Thou would'ſt abuſe me (replyed the Prince) only to aſſwage my grief; but if I find no other Green Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ins, I ſhall give no faith to any thing thou ſayeſt. At theſe words he endeavered to appear Blith and Gay, as he did before, and with a Countenance full of mirth and jollity, though his heart were heavy, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to ſeat the reſt of his Ladies on Horſe-back. He was come now to the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154286:24"/>very laſt, without finding any other Green Stockings but his Miſtreſſes, and the fear he ſhould fail of finding any other, hindred him from caſting up his eyes on her whoſe Leggs he only look'd on, without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whoſe they were; he was much ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to find Stockins and Garters both to be like thoſe <hi>Philemon</hi> had deſcribed. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemon,</hi> who thought of nothing more then relieving the Prince from the trouble he had put him, and making it appear he had no intention to deceive him, kept ſtill his Eyes caſt downwards; ſo that at the ſame time both he and the Prince cryed out they had found what they ſought for, if their joy were great, their amazement was no leſs, when lifting up their Eyes, almoſt both at a time they perceived. I believe you are very impatient now to know, and that your curioſity would be very burdenſome to you, if I ſhould long delay it. It was <hi>Philemons</hi> wife, which fight made him look as like a Coxcomb, as indeed he was. The Prince appeared as much amazed as he; but yet could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear laughing from the bottom of his heart. The Srory goes no farther, and ſince I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154286:25"/>have promiſed to write you nothing but truth, I will add nothing of my own, though it were eaſie to invent a thouſand fine things on ſo delicate an occaſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Duke <hi>de Feûillade,</hi> of the illuſtrious houſe <hi>D'Buſton</hi> ſo conſiderable, for the many Hero's iſſued from that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; and for that great Maſter of <hi>Rhodes</hi> of the ſame name, and ſo renowned in his own perſon, and ſo well known in the <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman</hi> Empire, who after a thouſand gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Actions done for the Honour and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the King his Maſter, had the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to ſee the Infidels chaſed out of <hi>Hungary,</hi> after their being defeated by thoſe brave <hi>French</hi> Troops he commanded, who following the Orders he gave them, and imitating his valour, defeated an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt innumerable Army, compoſed of the choiſeſt Forces of the <hi>Muſulmen;</hi> he, whoſe name is at this day ſo famous, through the whole Empire of the <hi>Turks,</hi> that ſame <hi>Mounſieur de Feûillade</hi> has been preſented by the King with the charge of Collonel of his Regiment of <hi>French</hi> Guards, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty did him the Honour to receive him in perſon into this Charge, which is ſo
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154286:25"/>much the more glorious, becauſe thoſe who enjoy it, receive thereby the Honours pavable to the Children of <hi>France.</hi> This Dukes Oath was received by the Marſhal Duke <hi>Du Ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sis,</hi> who was choſen out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the Marſhals in <hi>France</hi> who are Commiſſaries of His Majeſties Forces. This Marſhal is famous for his great Employs, for many Towns and Battails won, for the Siege of <hi>Roſes,</hi> where the Over flowings of the Waters, and all the Inconveniences of a hard ſeaſon, ſeemed to have conſpired together to oppoſe his Succeſs: yet though he aſſailed that City with fewer forces then defended it, his valour made the King Maſter of it, which his Majeſty recompenſed with the ſtaff of Marſhal of <hi>France.</hi> This great Captain is likewiſe famous for the gain of the glorious Battel of <hi>Rochel,</hi> which he won with ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and which decided the fortune of the Realm in a time wherein the Civil Wars had wrought ſo much confuſion. 'Twas this Battel diſperſed the Enemies of <hi>France,</hi> and made the frontiers of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom the Barriers againſt the Enterprizes of the Revolted Party.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:154286:26"/>
               <p>Some days paſt was acted on the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre of the <hi>Hoſtel de Burgogne,</hi> a Tragedy called <hi>Bajazet,</hi> which has gain'd the repute of an excellent Work, and you perhaps will think it ſo, when you hear 'tis a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Mounſieur <hi>Racines,</hi> ſince no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is moſt accompliſhed comes from the Pen of that Eminent Author. The Subject of the Tragedy is Turkiſh, as the Author ſays in his Preface: I will tell in two words what I could learn of that Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from the Hiſtorians of the Country, by which you may judge of the Admirable Genius of Poeſie, that without taking any thing elſewhere, could form ſo excellent a Tragedy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amurath</hi> had three Brothers when he went to beſiege <hi>Babylon,</hi> two he cauſed to be ſtrangled, neither of which was called <hi>Bajazet,</hi> the third was ſaved from his fury, becauſe he had no children to ſucceed in the Empire. This <hi>Grand Signior</hi> carried with him in that Voyage his favourite Sultaneſs. The Grand <hi>Vizier</hi> who was called <hi>Mahomet Baſha</hi> went likewiſe, as we may ſee in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation writ by a Turk of the <hi>Seraglio,</hi> and tranſlated into French by <hi>Mounſieur du Loir</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:154286:26"/>who was then at <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> and this was that Great <hi>Vizier</hi> who began the aſſault of that famous Town towards the <hi>Levant,</hi> with the Governour of <hi>Greece, Ali Baſha,</hi> the Son of <hi>Arlan,</hi> and the <hi>Aga</hi> of the Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizaries with his Regiment. At his return he entred triumphantly into <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> as his Maſter had done ſome days before. Yet the Author of <hi>Bajazet</hi> does ingeniouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make him ſtay at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> under the name of <hi>Achomat,</hi> to favour the deſigns of <hi>Roxana,</hi> who is here found in the <hi>Seraglio</hi> at <hi>Byzantium,</hi> though ſhe were indeed in his Highneſs Camp, and all this to raiſe <hi>Baja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zet</hi> to the Empire, whoſe name is very well invented. The third Brother of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan <hi>Amurath</hi> which remained, and eſcaped his wrath, was called <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> whom this cruel Emperour had the barbarous thoughts of deſtroying in that extream ſickneſs which ſeized him, and of which he died, with deſign (ſay they) to leave for Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor the young <hi>Muſtapha Capoudan Baſſa</hi> his Favourite, whom he had given in marriage to an onely daughter he had by his beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Sultaneſs. I cannot yield to them who think this piece expreſſes not enough
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154286:27"/>of the Turkiſh nature. There are <hi>Turks</hi> truly Gallant; and ſince it pleaſes, no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter how; nor coſts it more when we are feigning, to invent honeſt and gentile Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, than thoſe barbarous ones which agree not with the humour of the Ladies of our Age, whom 'tis a thing of the greateſt Importance to pleaſe. Gallantry, Bravery, and Goodneſs, are not things without Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Examples; and we have a very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Hiſtory in a Letter of <hi>Mounſieur de Loir</hi> writ to <hi>Mounſieur de Charpentier</hi> in 1641, which it's poſſible you would not be diſpleaſed if I ſhould rehearſe to you: ſome of it you ſhall have. He ſays, ſpeaking of a Friend of his newly arrived at <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was no ſooner got hither, but within three days a Lady gave him private notice of the inclination ſhe had for him; ſhe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one of her Companions to throw into his Windows Citrons ſtuck with Cloves, which are here the firſt Letters and Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of Love, and he finding the ſweetneſs of being beloved, anſwered with the ſame fervency the paſſion of her that loved him. She was a young Turkiſh Damſel of very
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154286:27"/>good quality called <hi>Zenakhoub,</hi> with whom he entertained an Amorous Commerce, of which the Hiſtory ſets down each particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. And ſurely if Adventures are thought the more pleaſing the more hazardous they are, few can claim preferrence to this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue; and though your ſelf ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſilence on me, I cannot forbear telling what at laſt happened to him, which is an Adventure worth relating, and cannot be unpleaſant in the reading. This raſh man had often diſguiſed himſelf like a Woman, to ſee his Love in Marriage-Aſſemblies, whither he was introduced by a Jew Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man intruſted with their ſecrets, and paſſed for a young Slave, ſhe ſaid ſhe had lately bought; his Youth, his Knowledge in the Countrey-Language, and the love he was inflamed with, were a favourable Paſport to him: But it was not long ere by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard-of Boldneſs and ſtrange Imprudence, going to ſee his Miſtreſs in mans Attire, he was like to loſe her, and be loſt. <hi>Zenak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houb</hi> had a long time been ſought in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, which ſhe had always concealed from this new Lover, reſolving never to tell it him till it was impoſſible for her to hinder
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154286:28"/>it longer, and now ſhe found it unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. She therefore ſent one morning (ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry early) to ſeek her new Love, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to come immediately with the Jew, whilſt the Turks were at their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers at break of day, for that ſhe feared ſhe ſhould never more have an opportunity to ſpeak with him. He was ſo ſhortned in time that he could not onely not diſguiſe his Sex, but had ſcarce leaſure to hide his own Habits under a Veſt, and to cover his Chin with a falſe Beard, and coming thus to <hi>Zenakhoub,</hi> was at his entrance amazed to find her in ſuch a ſerious meditation, but was much more when with many ſighs and interrupting ſobs ſhe told him of her Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and that ſhe onely ſent for him to take her laſt leave of him. He was aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at firſt, not being able to ſpeak a word, ſadneſs had ſo ſeiz'd his Soul: but during his ſilence, his Eyes gave evidence to <hi>Zenakhoub</hi> of the extream Grief he felt within. At laſt, both having for a good while entertained each other by looks, <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nakhoub</hi> with a great ſigh gave him notice 'twas time to part. I'll not tell you what they might ſay on this occaſion, for beſides
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154286:28"/>the recital would be too long, I will eaſe you of the grief I felt, when he made me the Rehearſal, and you may imagine that, but you cannot think what happened to them: He held <hi>Zenakhoub</hi> faſt by the hand, and he has ſwore to me that he thought ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily the fire of his kiſſes would have burnt her, if the tears he had ſhed from above, had not allayed and moderated their flame. To ſpeak all in a word, that at laſt the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences of his love had tranſported him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond thoſe bounds of reſpect which that virtuous Maid had ſet him, and within which he had always kept; he would have kiſt her mouth, but ſhe who felt her Soul almoſt yielding to her Paſſion, and her Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon now at laſt gaſp, fearing her Reſiſtance would at length too weakly defend her Modeſty, with a ſtrange and ſudden mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion drew forth a Dagger ſhe had at her Girdle, and preſenting it to him, conjured him by all the moſt obliging Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, rather to take away her Life, than attempt to offend her Honour. All our Lovers heat at this was turn'd to Ice, but being again by little and little warmed with this Amorous Conteſtation, as he was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154286:29"/>about to diſarm her, preſſing down her hand, he ſtruck the Dagger into her Thigh, ſo that what with the ſight o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her Bloud, and the other Agitations of her Soul, ſhe fell into a ſwound. The ſhreek he gave, ſeeing her in that condition, was heard by the Woman of the Houſe, who run in preſently, to whom they could not refuſe opening the Chamber-door, but before they got in, <hi>Zenakhoub</hi>'s Nurſe had ſhut up in an Alcove him that had been the cauſe of all this noiſe; and the blow ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving onely raced the Skin, thoſe that found it having carried <hi>Zenakhoub</hi> into a Balcony to give her freſh air, imputed it onely to a little faint-heartedneſs. Mean time, ſome were run to look for her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who came in great haſte, and found her Daughter juſt recovering her ſpirits with the help of cold Water thrown into her face: but ſhe was about to fall again into her ſwoun, upon ſeeing her ſelf in her Mothers Arms, and in the doubts and fears ſhe was in for her Lover. 'Twas well for her ſhe was thought to be ſo weak, ſhe had otherwiſe given too apparent Teſtimonies of the cauſe of her trouble; but before
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154286:29"/>ſhe was fully come to her ſelf, ſhe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her Mother teſtified more kindneſs than anger, and judged both by it and by her lamenting her miſhap, that ſhe knew neither of the Author nor Cauſe. Yet ſhe was not out of fear for her Lover, who for his part paſt the time no better, and heard no one come near the place where he was, but he imagined they came to him; and he gave himſelf over to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, when the Jew feigning to look out ſome Cloaths, threw him a Womans Habit to diſguiſe himſelf in. I believe now that you would be glad to be rid of your fears you are in for him: and to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it will be enough to tell you, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by that diſguiſe he got out of the houſe: but his love not thus ſatisfied, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed him to another hazard again, to ſee <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nakhoub,</hi> before he left her for ever; and, which I almoſt tremble at when I but think of it, made him take the boldneſs to go in where ſhe was, and to whiſper ſomething in the Jew's Ear, as if he had been a Slave ſent to her about ſome buſineſs. If <hi>Zenak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houb</hi>'s Mother had not been otherwiſe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd, or prepoſſeſs'd with grief, or had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154286:30"/>taken the leaſt notice how the Jew was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed, and grew pale at his entrance, or how her Daughter changed Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which on a ſudden was all in a flame, it had poſſibly put any other thoughts into her head than what ſhe feared, that this ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den change was a ſymptome of <hi>Zenakhoub</hi>'s diſtemperature: But ſhe ſuſpected nothing, and the ſick Lady having called the Jew to her, as if ſhe deſired ſome aſſiſtance from her, to help her to raiſe her head upon the pillow; ſhe commanded her immediately to carry away that raſh man, to give ſome eaſe to her Spirit toſſed and perplexed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Fear and Love. They departed immediately, and <hi>Zenakhoub</hi>'s Wound be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more favourable than hurtful, ſerved onely for a pretence to retard the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
               <p>But let us return to the Author of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jazet,</hi> whoſe Work has occaſioned the recital of this Adventute. I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay to you of his Worth. It is ſo Great, that there is no place left on <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> worthy to offer him. His Friends would ſeat him between <hi>Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:154286:30"/>and <hi>Euripides,</hi> in whoſe Works <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes Laertius</hi> would make us believe <hi>Socrates</hi> had the greateſt ſhare in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blimeſt parts: The Rivals of this <hi>French Euripides</hi> or <hi>Socrates,</hi> would I doubt not be willing to ſee him gone to thoſe great Perſonages among the Greeks, though upon condition that his memory were as glorious as theirs ever deſerved to be.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>9 <hi>January</hi> 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:154286:31"/>
               <head>Letter III.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot tell, <hi>Madam,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my Letters have the good fortune to pleaſe you, but I aſſure you, I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diligent to inform my ſelf of the moſt curious No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties, and moſt ſurprizing Adventures; and I believe this wherewith I am about to entertain you, will appear no leſs wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than the former. It happened ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſince in one of the Provinces of this Kingdom, where it is yet the whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Celiantes</hi> a Perſon of Quality, handſome, witty, valiant, and who had given Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Judgment and Valour in an Age
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154286:31"/>when others ſeem but to peep into the World, fell deeply in love with the young <hi>Lydiana.</hi> You may think now I am go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to paint her out like a <hi>Heroine</hi> in a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, and intend to tell you ſhe was the faireſt Perſon in the World; but ſince I am to relate a true ſtory, I will leave the Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity of thoſe pretty Imbelliſhments to the Ingenious Inventers of Romances, wherewith the pleaſant Wits of <hi>France</hi> have often diverted the whole World. All that I can ſay for <hi>Lydiana</hi>'s advantage, is, that ſhe had a well-ſhap'd Body, and had a great deal of Wit; and if ſhe did not paſs for a Beauty, ſhe muſt needs have ſome pleaſing Features, which though all the World could not find out, appeared ſo at leaſt in the Eyes of her Lover, if it be true that Proverbs never lie. <hi>Lydiana</hi> was of Quality, and had a great Portion, and beſides was to be Heireſs to two of her Relations, who had the repute to be the richeſt men of their Country. You know <hi>Madam,</hi> that there cannot be much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit; thoſe that appear rich in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, are ſo indeed. Their Wealth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to the Eyes of all the World, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154286:32"/>their Lands are a ſubſtance not to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away in a night. <hi>Lydiana</hi>'s great Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and the hopes of thoſe great Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances like to fall to her, gain'd her an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible number of Suiters of all Qualities, among whom <hi>Celiante</hi> appeared not the leaſt paſſionate. Since ſhe was not fair, and had the wit to know ſhe was not ſo, ſhe reſolved to diſpoſe her heart to him who mixed the leaſt Intereſt and hopes of Gain with his Love. This was a hard thing to find out. Men know ſo well how to diſſemble; and when there is Intereſt in the caſe, there are few but find preſently the way to become <hi>Hypocrites. Lydiana</hi> after having the beſt ſhe could examined them all, and tried them by a thouſand cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning practices, believed <hi>Celiantes</hi> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſteſt man of them all; and judging him the moſt upright and leaſt covetous, thought ſhe ought to diſpoſe of her heart to him: He perceived her inclination to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, which made him preſs forward his love the more, and he ſoon obtained what he wiſhed; there can little reſiſtance be found after ſuch Reſolutions as <hi>Lydia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>'s. The Intelligence formed between
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154286:32"/>them was ſoon found out by the reſt of the Suitors of this Ingenious Lady, and her Relations were not long ignorant of it. The Choice of <hi>Lydiana</hi>'s Heart agreed not with Theirs, they had not taken ſuch precaution in making it as ſhe had done, but the richeſt ſeemed to them moſt worthy to have her. I will not relate to you the croſſes theſe Lovers met with, nor what <hi>Lydiana</hi> ſuffered between Love and her Friends; few Amorous Hiſtories but will ſupply you with ſuch Traverſes. I will be ſatisfied to tell you, that after many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes the prudent <hi>Lydiana</hi> knew ſo well how to manage things with her Relations, that ſoon after they not onely yielded ſhe ſhould not marry whom they had firſt pitched upon, but likewiſe conſented ſhe ſhould eſpouſe <hi>Celiantes.</hi> Nothing could be more happy than the firſt years of their Marriage, they loved like Lovers; nor was there ever ſeen a more perfect Union, which might happily have endured longer, if the Eyes of the young <hi>Eliſa</hi> had not come to diſturb their Content and Quiet. Never was there Woman more ſubtile, nor practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed more Arts and Devices to pleaſe. She
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:154286:33"/>pleaſed indeed <hi>Celiantes</hi> unhappily for him, and knew how to allure him with ſo much Cunning and Artifice, that he loſt by lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and little all the love he had for his wife, he preſently forgot his good Humour and Complaiſance towards her, from thence paſſed to Indifference, and his Indifference ſoon turned to Neglect. Neither did miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs ſtop here, but as theſe Miſſes are not content with mens hearts, but onely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject them to draw in ſomewhat elſe; <hi>Celi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antes</hi> found himſelf inſenſibly engaged to make every day new Preſents to <hi>Eliſa,</hi> and that cunning Whore had ſuch ſly contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to bring occaſions about, that they ſeemed as it were to preſent themſelves. You may eaſily gueſs <hi>Lydiana</hi> bore not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry patiently both the loſs of <hi>Celiantes</hi> heart, and the conſumption of their Eſtate. There were many ſtorms about it, that made a thundring noiſe, but <hi>Lydiana</hi> loving her Husband paſſionately, ſtill appeaſed all theſe vehemencies by a compliant ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Till in the end things grew to that height of diſtreſs, ſhe could no longer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, but was forced loudly to complain; for blows and ill uſage followed his Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:154286:33"/>Neglect, and waſte of Eſtate. The Clamour <hi>Lydiana</hi> made, gladded inſtead of afflicting <hi>Celiantes,</hi> he took thence occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to leave his Wife, and to go live with his Miſs. <hi>Lydiana,</hi> who now began to believe ſhe had not ſo much love as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for her Husband, becauſe ſhe had no reaſon to love him, was not ſenſible at once of all her Grief, and all her Love. Nay, now ſhe began to think ſhe might come to hate him, becauſe ſhe found her heart endeavouring to entertain a hatred of him: Yet again ſhe would have ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of kindneſs which made her endure all the moſt violent Torments of Jealouſie, which at laſt threw her into ſo furious a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, that at length ſhe determined to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute what I am about to tell you. She feigned her ſelf ſick, and that ſhe daily grew worſe and worſe, having corrupted a Doctor to aver the ſame thing. She deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then to ſee her Husband, as being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to die till ſhe were reconciled with him. He was ſent for in haſte to the Countrey, where he lived with <hi>Eliſa:</hi> His Intereſt made him come with all ſpeed and diligence, for he had yet ſome conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:154286:34"/>things to hope from his Wife, if he made his peace with her before ſhe died. He was no ſooner arrived, but he begg'd her pardon, which ſhe as ſoon granted him, at leaſt in appearence; and they ſeemed the beſt agreed people in the World. After the ſecond day ſhe deſired he would lie in her Chamber, and not at all leave her, he yielded to her requeſt, and a Bed was ſet up for him near to hers. Short time after, ſhe declared her ſelf ſomewhat bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that there was no neceſſity for any other than her Husband to lie in the room, 'twas thought ſhe had ſomething in private to ſay to him; ſo at laſt they conſented, though with ſome oppoſition, for fear ſhe might be taken ill in the night. She ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed extreamly kind that evening to her Husband; but when he was faſt aſleep, ſhe riſes and hides the Key of the Door, then places ſome Faggots in the middle of the Chamber with the Tables and Chairs, and ſo ſets fire to it in many places, and to the Matreſſes of the two Beds. There was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready a great flame, when <hi>Celiantes</hi> awoke: he would have run ſtraight to the door, but the ſmoke and fire hindred his finding it;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:154286:34"/>and if he had found it, it had been to ſmall purpoſe. <hi>You muſt die,</hi> ſaid <hi>Lydiana,</hi> ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him by the Arm; <hi>and though thou wouldeſt not live with me, I will let thee ſee I have love enough for thee to die with thee.</hi> She added ſomewhat elſe, and he anſwered her; but thoſe who came to help them could neither hear what it was, nor prevent the fires conſuming both of them. <hi>Eliſa</hi> was ſo penitent for having been the cauſe of ſo cruel an accident, that ſhe went into a Nunnery, but all her penitence for her Crimes will not reſtore Life to theſe two unfortunate Perſons, whom Love has made periſh in flames much fiercer than his own.</p>
               <p>There is nothing talked of here but plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and divertiſements, nor were ever Balls or Muſick ſo much in the mode. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medians have lately acted here a piece ſtuffed full of them, which is intituled <hi>The Marriage of Bacchus and Ariana;</hi> the Songs took mightily, the Airs being compoſed by the famous <hi>Monſieur de Moliere,</hi> whoſe abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are every where known, and who has been for many years imployed to compoſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154286:35"/>the Aires for the Kings Balads. He is the Author of <hi>The loves of the Sun,</hi> which got ſo much fame the year laſt paſt, and which this preſent Winter has been the buſineſs of the Theatre; for almoſt two Months I will ſay no more of his works; he is too much my friend, and therefore the praiſes I give him, may perhaps be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted.</p>
               <p>After having undergone the troubles of a long Voyage, and ſuffered all thoſe inconveniencies which the Sea oppreſſes them with, whoſe tempers cannot away with it; <hi>Monſieur Curtin</hi> is at laſt happily arrived in <hi>Sweden.</hi> Though he be yet but young, he manages all truſts impoſed on him with the prudence and diſcretion of the moſt ancient men, and that have been the longeſt verſt in imployes. And we muſt needs believe his merits to be great, if we judge of them by the many Services, wherein the King has made uſe of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Duke <hi>D'Eſtrees,</hi> as intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in Affairs of Counſel, as of War, parted ſome dayes ſince extraordinary Embaſſador for <hi>Rome;</hi> he is Son to the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:154286:35"/>late <hi>Marſhal D'Eſtrees,</hi> ſo famous for the War of the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> which his diſcontents conceived againſt the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> made him ſtir up, and who in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Embaſſes had favourable ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Jan.</hi> 16. 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="letter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:154286:36"/>
               <head>Letter IV.</head>
               <p>THough there be nothing more ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry then Compliment, nothing for the moſt part is more troubleſome and uſeleſs. I therefore intreat you Madam to excuſe them at the front of my Letters, and that I may immediately fall to the Story I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to relate, and take now one, which I'le aſſure you is very new.</p>
               <p>One of thoſe young people, who pretend to know all things, and yet do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, of thoſe able Coxcombs who ſpend moſt part of their lives in waiting for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployes, having devoured all his income, which was not much, flattering himſelf ſtill with the hopes of a great fortune, at length finding himſelf ſomewhat oppreſſed for want of means, believed, that he might more commodiouſly wait for an imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to raiſe him to the heights he dream'd of, if he married, and eat up a Wives fortune, as he had done his own.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:154286:36"/>His pretended endowments ſoon made him find out a woman, and the mighty things he boaſted himſelf capable of, made it be thought, that if he could but one day get the leaſt imploy in the Treaſury, he might in a little time gain two or three Millions of Eſtate. He wanted not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous examples of his prodigious fortunes, to authorize his great hopes, and he made it evident, that all thoſe who had gained ſuch great fortunes, were but Aſles and Fops in Compariſon of him. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of her he deſired to marry, ſwallowed this Gudgeon, and believed, that if one day he came into the management of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he might give Commiſſions to all their Family, and one of theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen fully relyed upon it, for three or four of his Children. And as many Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews. There was likewiſe one of the richeſt amongſt them, who being to give ſome recompence to a ſervant had waited on him for ten years, opened his Purſe-ſtrings, which he had already untyed, and promiſed him a Commiſſion of a hundred Crowns Rent. The man accepted the Bargain, and fancyed to himſelf, that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:154286:37"/>after that Commiſſion, he ſhould get ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that ſoon after he ſhould have his Coach, and poſſibly in a little more time might buy ſome Marquiſate; nay, he did not deſpair, but it might come to a Dutchy; upon theſe ſplendid hopes of the whole family of the future Spouſe, all whoſe Relations had their heads filled with Chimera's, the Marriage was agreed upon, celebrated and conſummated all at once; ſo earneſt were theſe imagining peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at it, and ſo fearful leaſt the main En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of ſuch great fortunes ſhould eſcape them, and their Family. There was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Feaſts and Rejoycings ſucceeded the Marriage, at which nothing was talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, but the future greatneſs of the new Husband, two or three Months paſſed in this manner, and no imployments came to ſupply the expence. The Relations of the Wife beſtirred themſelves mightily to get one for their new Kinſman; they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed their Friends, but with all their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitations they could get only a Serving-man; which he refuſed with much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, in the mean time the Portion he got with his wife waſted, and he became al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:154286:37"/>as beggerly as before; and now his vexation was the more, becauſe he had now a Wife to maintain, whoſe humour is a little whoriſh, and who loved to live high. The Gallants came, and it being now much to the purpoſe, were well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not by the Husband; for he was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally jealous; but they told him, That thoſe that came thither were perſons of quality, and who might help him to an imployment. Being in theſe ſtraits he was forced to make a virtue of neceſſity; having hopes to get a Commiſſion by their means; but though all theſe reaſons made him ſuffer their coming thither, he could not do it but with much perplexity, and his continual preſence, growing troubleſome to them, there was one, who to get rid of him, gave him an imployment in the Countrey. He was dubious at firſt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhould accept it, not being willing to go from his Wife; but in the end he was perſwaded to part, the imployment being conſiderable. They told him, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune offered not her ſelf every day, and that who once let her eſcape, did not eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find her again. To it then he goes, but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:154286:38"/>with much reluctancy; ſo much he feared his Wives growing more whoriſh in his abſence; he was not deceived in it, and had notice of it by one of thoſe imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent friends, who giving advice to Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands of what their Wives do, wrong them more then their Wives themſelves, though all they ſay of them be true. This poor Husband endured much ſorrow, with vexing that his Wife enjoyed more pleaſure then he; he was many times about to quit his imployment, and come to be her Goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; but having no reaſonable pretence, he ſaw well that his return would be to no other purpoſe then to make his misfortunes more publick. This made him change his determinations, but as a jealous man continually meditating, it came one day into his head, to find out a way that his Wife ſhould no longer be ſo fair, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that with her beauty ſhe would looſe many of her lovers; and this was the Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem he concluded of, he ſent her a Packet by the Poſt, into which he made up a very fine Box of Gold. This Box was filled with Gunpowder, and ſo order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that when the Scrue was opened it
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:154286:38"/>ſhould take fire by means of a Stone pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed to that purpoſe. This preſent was delivered ſafe to the party to whom it was deſigned; but it was given to her in his preſence from whom her Husband held his Commiſſion, he thought it a Picture ſent from ſome other Lover, and earneſtly ſnatches the Box, but his Jealous Curioſity was ſoon puniſhed, for in opening it, it wrought the ſame effect on him the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band deſign'd it ſhould have done on his Wife. This Adventure became a Town-talk. The Gallant believing the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band had ſent the Box, and ſoon after took away his Commiſſion, on a falſe pretence of ill management. He returned to his Wife, where he and the whole Family are expecting new Commiſſions, which may one day put them in a condition to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their mighty hopes.</p>
               <p>Mounſieur the <hi>Marquiſs de Villars</hi> has made his Publick Entry into <hi>Madrid</hi> with a great deal of Magnificence: You know he is a very comely Gentleman, excellently humoured, and of a tried Valour; and the choice made of him to be Ambaſſadour in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:154286:39"/>
                  <hi>Spain,</hi> where ſuch delicacy of Judgment is required, is a certain evidence of his Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mounſieur de Pompone</hi> is lately returned from <hi>Sweden,</hi> and has already taken his Oath as Secretary of State: His Worth is known to all the World, ſince 'tis that has raiſed him to this Dignity. There is no perſon but is perſwaded he will behave himſelf worthy of the Choice made of him by the Greateſt and Wiſeſt King of the World; and great things are expected from him. He writes with more ſpirit and life than can be obſerved in any of the moſt ſtudied Letters of our Academians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="letter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:154286:39"/>
               <head>Letter V.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince I have told you in my laſt I would uſe no more Complements, but begin all my Letters with the Stories I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to relate; I will keep my word with you, and begin.</p>
               <p>An old covetous Fellow, who had yet no Children, and who was deſperate fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of any expence, was almoſt ready to run mad, when his Wife told him ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved ſhe had conceived; he began to caſt up in his Brain all that a Child would coſt him, till it came to be thirty years of Age, and framed ſo exact an accompt of it, that he reckoned likewiſe the food they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:154286:40"/>took in their Mothers Bellies, alledging that Women with Child eat both for Themſelves and their Children: He ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded together all theſe ſums, and then caſt up how much they would purchaſe, if he laid them out in Rents, and how much the Intereſt upon Intereſt would produce. He found the total to amount ſo high, that he repented a thouſand and a thouſand times the day that ever he was married, and made a full reſolution never to attempt getting any more Children, deeming it a pleaſure unbecoming a diſcreet and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding man. Whilſt he was making theſe Accounts and theſe Reflections, his Wife perceived certainly ſhe was with Child, and no more doubt to be made of it; ſhe told it to her griping Husband, whoſe grief was twice as much as it had been before, and from that very minute he began ſeveral Retrenchments in his Houſe, that his Thrift might help bear the charges of the coming Infant; but how gripple ſoever he were, he could ſave little this way, ſince rather than a ſuperfluity, there was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready a want of many neceſſary things. But if his torment were great, to ſee his Wife
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:154286:40"/>with Child, it was doubled and redoubled, when about the ſixth month ſhe told him that ſhe believed ſhe was with Child with two, and that many knowing Women doubted it; he was then ready to hang himſelf; but one we call a Man-midwife, a Friend of his, eas'd him of this vexation, by aſſuring him the contrary. Soon after, ſcolding with his Wife, he told her 'twas convenient to conſider which would coſt leaſt, to bring up a Boy or a Girl; and after having well examined the matter, and reckoned at their fingers ends the expence of one and the other, they found that a Boy would coſt leaſt, becauſe he might make his own fortune; but the Father and the Mother muſt make out the Girles, by providing her a portion. I will have you then ſaid the Husband bring me a Boy. That is neirher in your power nor mine, reply'd the Wife. It ſhall be as I tell you, replyed the Husband. It may be ſo, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, anſwered the Wife, if Nature has thought good to make one. Let Nature have made one or no, cry'd the old Wreth in wrath, I ſay you ſhall be brought to Bed of a Boy, or at leaſt the Child you bring
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:154286:41"/>forth ſhall appear to the eyes of the world whatever I will have it to be: for if you be brought to bed of a Girl, we will ſay 'tis a Boy, and bring it up under that habit. The Woman was forced to conſent, and all the reſt of her time they fortified them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this Reſolution. Her hour being come, ſhe was brought to bed of a Girl, and to make it be believed a Boy, they took thoſe courſes they had before contrived. All that ſaw it were deceived, and when it grew in years many young Maids fell in love with it. This young Beauty being ill treated by her Father, and worſe fed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to leave the Covetous Miſer, and as ſoon as ſhe found her ſelf able to carry a Muſquet, enliſted her ſelf and came to the Army, where in the firſt Field ſhe made her ſelf be taken notice of. All that ſaw her, took a liking to her, they could give no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for, and ſhe had a kind of modeſt and obliging carriage, which hindred thoſe who were Enemies to Worth in all others, from envying her. She was always very reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and though ſhe knew not her ſelf what ſhe was, ſhe lived as if ſhe deſigned a concealment; and it ſucceeded ſo happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:154286:41"/>that never any ſuſpected it. She was not yet grown to all the marks neceſſary to diſtinguiſh her: for though ſhe was pretty large, ſhe was very young, and had ſtrength enough to undergo the toyls of War. In the firſt Garriſon where ſhe quartered, her Landlords Daughter fell deſperately in love with her, and fearing her ſelf to be already with Child by a Lover that was lately dead, and willing to hide her ſhame by clapping up a Match with this Object of her New Love, ſhe omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nothing might gain his good Will, doing a thouſand obliging things for this fair Souldier, to bring her deſign to effect: ſhe followed him every where, gave him meetings in an hundred different places, that all the World might take notice of her love, and ſpeak of it to her Father. Her plot took, for thoſe who ſpoke of it told him, That after ſo much talk of this her Paſſion, he would never find any one would marry her, and therefore to ſalve his Reputation, he muſt of force give her to him ſhe loved ſo fervently. The Good Man was of their opinion, and after having a little chid his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:154286:42"/>and given her ſome good Leſſons, he talked with her about marrying the young Souldier quartered with him. It is to be obſerved that this Diſguiſed Maid paſſed for a young Lad of a good Family, and pretty rich, who was come to the Army without his Friends Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and this was the chief Motive to make mine Hoſt reſolve to give him his Daughter. I will not trouble you with all that paſſed till the wedding-day, but onely bring this new-married Couple to Bed: There 'tis I believe you expect them. The Bride's heart went pit-a-pat out of fear her Husband ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover another had reap'd thoſe Favours ſhould have been reſerved for him: But that fear ſoon vaniſhed, when ſhe percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved too clearly that he was in a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to examine nothing; thus from one danger ſhe apprehended, ſhe fell into a worſe, from which ſhe would ſoon have with-drawn her ſelf, if ſhe had not been with Child, by diſcovering all. But however, ſhe did nothing; and was ſo long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting with her ſelf what to do, that her Great Belly appeared; and now ſhe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:154286:42"/>thought it too late to ſpeak: But un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily for her, as ſhe was in her Ninth Moneth, and a bed with her pretended Husband, one of her Kinſwomen came into the Chamber while they were aſleep, and putting her hand on the bed to wake her Couſin, who ſtirr'd not at the noiſe ſhe made coming in, ſhe met with the Breſts of the Maiden Husband, which lay uncovered, and preſently it was known ſhe was a Woman, for the Kinſwomans aſtoniſhment was ſo great, that ſhe cried our aloud what ſhe had diſcovered. This is the original of that Adventure has been of late ſo much talked of, and which has made ſo many ignorant people publiſh, That one Maid got another with Child.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mounſieur</hi> the Chancellour finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf much afflicted with his Diſtemper, has ordered his Children to return the Seals into his Majeſties hands, fearing leſt his Malady ſhould hinder him from ſerving him with the ſame application he had done for this thirty nine years, in which he had officiated in this important Charge. Mounſieur the Duke of <hi>Coaſlin</hi> carried
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:154286:43"/>word of it, and did it in a way very ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory to his Majeſty. I know not, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> whether you have ever underſtood all the Worth of that Duke; his Valour is well known, and he eſteemed one of the beſt men in the world, and the moſt offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Friend, earneſt to do kindneſſes, and joyful when he has done them. As for his internal parts, the place he has in the Academy is a ſufficient Teſtimony of them.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>30 <hi>January</hi> 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="letter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:154286:43"/>
               <head>Letter VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am very doubtful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam whether this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will have the good fortune to pleaſe you. and I have a great deal of reaſon to doubt it, ſince inſtead of finding as in the precedent, ſome divertizing Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, you will underſtand that ſuch is my grief for the death of the good Chancellor, that I am not in a condition to relate Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. That great Chancellor is now no more, nor had death ſo long ſpared him, but to make <hi>France</hi> more ſenſible of his loſs. He was a man of eminent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, of admirable eloquence, and a Prudence often put to the teſt in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:154286:44"/>of two of the greateſt Kings in the world he was a great Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor to learning, the Protector of all knowing men, and for a Crown to all his glories, he was the ſtrongeſt prop and buttreſs of the Church that any age has known. Nor do I ſay this but upon the credit of many Prelates, who publiſh it as a truth. Never did man better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Juſtice, Ordinances and Laws of the Kingdom, nor appeared more to value able men of whatever profeſſion. He ſought with much labour and diligence to underſtand what belonged to his em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, or to thoſe Counſels he was obliged to give in affairs of State, often acknowledging the ſearch he had made of perſons who might give him the leaſt light, though he had much more underſtanding then thoſe he conſulted with.</p>
               <p>But if death hath raviſhed from us one great Miniſter. The King has made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by giving <hi>Mounſier de Louvoy</hi> the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Miniſter of State, he ows this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement only to his worth; for it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, that his vigilance, exactneſs and good conduct in all things depending on
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:154286:44"/>his miniſtry, have made his Majeſty diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in him the moſt accompliſhed poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, which obliged him to make choiſe of him to aſſiſt in all Counſels in the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Miniſter of State. Though he be yet very young, there ſhines in him all the prudence and ſagacity of a Counſellor grown gray in affairs. All his actions are beautified with an incorruptible fidelity, and an exemplary ſtrictneſs, which may be obſerved in his ſeventy towards his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants, when they at any time faulter in their duty, he is always ready to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud and recompence good ſervice, but he is inexorable when men ſtray from their duty. The choice he makes of thoſe he puts into imployments under him, juſtifies the good choiſe the King made when he left things to hir diſpoſe, and daily intruſts him with affairs of moſt concern both to the publick, and to his own particular glory.</p>
               <p>Death the day before yeſterday ſnatcht from us Madam the Princeſs of <hi>Conty,</hi> ſhe was as you very well know daughter of Count <hi>Martinozzi,</hi> and of a Siſter of the late Cardinal <hi>Mazarine.</hi> Though nature
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:154286:45"/>had given her a great portion of beauty, her devotion made her neglect it, ſhe lived with <hi>Mounſier</hi> the Prince of <hi>Conty</hi> with that reſpect made her reguarded with much kindneſs and conſideration. Her great piety none are ignorant of, and her plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Almes could not be hid from the world. Her care in bringing up her Children was worthy ſo great a Princeſs, and the fruits of her endeavours may be ſeen in thoſe little Princes, in whom may be obſerved qualities above the uſual reach of ſuch ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſpirits.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>February</hi> 6. 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="letter">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:154286:45"/>
               <head>Letter VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Believe, Madam, fame has already given you an account, how ſince the death of the late Lord Chancellor, the King would himſelf take the Charge of Keeper of his Seals; but perhaps you have not yet heard, that the firſt day he took that care upon him, he imployed himſelf at it for near ſeven hours, and yet that hindred him not from holding the ſame day two Counſels of more then three hours and a halfe each. Never was Prince heard of, that took ſo much pains, or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured ſo hard for the good of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, his Majeſty has ſince named to have
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:154286:46"/>care of the Seal with deliberative voice, ſix ordinary Counſellors of ſtate, who are the <hi>Meſieurs D' Aligre, de Seve, Poncet, Boucherat, Puſſort,</hi> and <hi>Voiſin;</hi> he has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated likewiſe fix Maſters of Requeſts, which are the <hi>Meſsieurs Barretin le Boulan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger de Haqueville, le Pelletier, de Faucon, de Lamoignon,</hi> and <hi>Pelliſon.</hi> The Kings prudence may be judged of by the merit of thoſe he has named.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur D' Aligre</hi> is of Sixty Nine years of Age, and Son of a Chancellor, he has been Fifty years in the Counſel, has paſſed through all Charges, and been a long time Director of the Finances; his honeſty and uprightneſs are known and eſteemed by all the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur de Seve</hi> has been Secretary of the Cloſet, Maſter of Requeſts, and ſince Provoſt of the Merchants; he is at this preſent one of the Eldeſt Councellors of State, and has ever been one of the moſt zealout Servants of his King.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:154286:46"/>
               <p>The many different Charges under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone by <hi>Monſieur Poncet,</hi> have got him a great fame, and made his merits be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur Boucherat</hi> is well known by the great imployments he has had, and the many important Commiſſions he has always diſcharged to his Majeſties content, particularly in <hi>Britany,</hi> where he has been often Commiſſioner of the States for the King, he is a man of great Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur Puſſort</hi> is eſtemable for many things, and particularly for the invention of new Laws and Ordinances, which may deliver the <hi>French</hi> from oppreſſion,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur Voiſin</hi> has Signalized him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in many occaſions, reſpecting his Miniſtry, he has been Provoſt of the Merchants, where he deſerved the place of Ordinary of the Counſel, with which he was honoured.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:154286:47"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur Barretin</hi> is ſometime ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from the Super-intendence of <hi>Poictou</hi> he is Maſter of the Requeſts, and Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the great Counſel, I know, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> you are ſenſible of his worth, and therefore ſhall ſay no more of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur le Boulange de Haqueville</hi> is a man whoſe uprightneſs is well known in the Council, he has a great deal of wit, and makes himſelf be diſtinguiſhed by a particular way of reporting affairs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur le Pelletier de la Houſſaye</hi> is fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, a good Judge, and who knows how to value a good Cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur de Lamoignon</hi> is Son to <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> the <hi>premier</hi> Preſident. The great worth of his Father, and the care he had of his Childrens Education, would ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently of themſelves ſpeak advantagiouſly of him, if he had not of himſelf given par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Evidences of his merit. He has Signalized himſelf in the Parliament, and continues to do ſo every day in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, thereupon his Majeſty has choſen him an Aſſiſtant of the Seal.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:154286:47"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur Pelliſſon</hi> is known by all the world, his judgment and his uprightneſs are indiſputable, and though he had eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where left Evidences of them, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours he continually is receiving from the King, would be an aſſured Teſtimony for him.</p>
               <p>The Young <hi>Marchioneſſe,</hi> whom you know very well, who began to play ſo well on the Lute, is fallen into deſpair ſome dayes ſince. <hi>Monſieur Gaultier,</hi> who taught her, had aſſured her ſhe ſhould in a little time play as well as Madam <hi>Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Lenclos.</hi> 'Twas a bold word that; but he was one might give deciſions in thoſe ſort of Affairs. Thoſe were the laſt words that great Maſter ſpoke about play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Lute; For at his going from this young <hi>Marchioneſſe,</hi> he fell ſick of a diſtemper, which he is ſince dead of. She no ſooner heard the News; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving her Lute ſhould not ſurvive ſo great a Maſter, ſhe broke it all in pieces, and has determined never to play more. I will not diſcant on this action, but leave you to judge of it. But if the death of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:154286:48"/>
                  <hi>Monſieur Gualtier</hi> hinders her from ever playing on the Lute, ſo well as <hi>Madam de Lenclos,</hi> ſhe may yet endeavour to reſemble her in her wit and judgment, with which you know that excellent perſon is infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well ſtored.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>February</hi> 13, 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="letter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:154286:48"/>
               <head>Letter VIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot tell, <hi>Madam,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you may have yet heard of any Adventure happened ſometime ſince in this City, and which has been occaſion of much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant diſcourſe this Carnaval in all the Balls at <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A young married man, being one after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon with ſome of his Friends, told them, that that Evening he had a Meeting at his houſe, and that he gave a Ball to a Siſter of his Wives, that ſojourned with her. One of the moſt pleaſant fellows of the Company perſwaded to go in Maſquarade, and told the young married man, His
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:154286:49"/>pleaſure would be much the greater, if he came along with them in a diſguiſe. He conſented, and they preſently ſent for Habits of Maſquerade. The Hour of the Ball being come, they all went thither, and their Gentee carriage made many Conqueſts. The young Huſband made one, which in the end pleaſed him not at all; for his Wife fell in love with him without knowing him, ſhe ſtaid not long before ſhe gave him ſigns of it, tenderly ſweezing his hand, and he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered his kindneſs in the moſt loving man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he could; for the Adventure had a little Chilled his Blood, and never was man ſo vexed to be taken for another; yet he was reſolved to ſee how far the buſineſs would go; but he found all things ſo well diſpoſed, that it was no mighty task to make himſelf happy. I mean hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in quality of Gallant, for he was not ſo as Husband. His wife, who had doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs heard ſome good Goſſips ſay, That a favourable occaſion muſt never be loſt; For it is a hard matter to find again thoſe we let ſcape, thought beſt to make uſe of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:154286:49"/>this opportunity which the Ball preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and ſince the confuſion of ſo many people as were there gave her the means of ſtealing ſafely from them, without being perceived; ſhe thought it a duty to love, and nature to ſlip àſide with her new Gallant, and 'twas no ſooner thought then done. She led him up a private pair of Stairs into a Chamber, where they could not be ſurprized. I will not tell you all that paſſed there; but the Lady was very well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented; yet it ſomewhat troubled her, that he would not ſpeak to her, and that for fear to be known he had put out the light before he unmatched himſelf. She asked him many times the reaſon of it. He would not then anſwer her; but as ſoon as he had proceeded far enough to convince her of diſloyalty, he broke ſilence, and began to reproch her with her falſeneſs. She was ſo much the more bold to anſwer him, becauſe there was no light to diſcover any change of Countenance, and having there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by time to recover from any ſurprize. She told him ſhe knew him as ſoon as he came into the houſe, and that ſhe only contrived
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:154286:50"/>this to laugh a little with him: He was not at all ſatisfied with theſe, but would, and will paſs for what other men are ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of being accounted; and though it were done by himſelf, yet he believed himſelf as ſubſtantial a Cuckold as any man in the world could make him. He would never ſee his Wife from that time, and deſigns to ſue out a ſeparation from her. I leave you to judge whether he or I have reaſon; and paſs to other News.</p>
               <p>The King willing to acknowledge the merits of <hi>Monſieur Pauchau,</hi> and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence his ſervices, gave him ſome days paſt a Commiſſion to be one of the Maſters of acccounts, and joyned a conſiderable ſum to that gift; his Majeſty likewiſe let him know, that he ſhould attend to the ſame ſervices under <hi>Monſieur Pompone,</hi> he had formerly done under <hi>Monſieur de Lyon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:154286:50"/>
               <p>The <hi>Meſsieurs de Vendoſme</hi> are late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly returned from <hi>Italy,</hi> where they have gained repute in all places where they have paſſed. The vivacity of their Spirits is a thing incredible, and and they compoſe Verſes with ſo much ſmoothneſs, as would make great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors jealous if their quality would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to do it often. <hi>Monſieur the Cardinal Patron,</hi> cauſed to be ſet up for them the repreſentation of an <hi>Opera,</hi> to give them ſome divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Judge by that, Madam, what conſiderable things theſe <hi>Opera</hi>'s are, when perſons of ſuch high quality are concerned in them, and honour them with their preſence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur de Camus</hi> has beſtowed on him by the King the Charge of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mier</hi> Preſident of the Court of Aydes, his merit muſt needs be extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſince he was preferred before ſo many deſerving perſons, and who had the ſame pretenſions. It is he, who
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:154286:51"/>was formerly Proctor General of the ſame Chamber.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>February</hi> 20, 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="letter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:154286:51"/>
               <head>Letter IX.</head>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam,</salute>
               <p> I am afraid that at opening this Letter, finding it ſo ſhort you will think me Idle: but pray conſider that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo in any thing relates to you, but throw all the fault on this Weeks bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs of News.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mounſieur Deſpincha</hi> Marquiſs of <hi>Ternes,</hi> of one of the beſt Families of <hi>Auvergne,</hi> Lieutenant General of the Kings Naval Forces and Galleys of <hi>France,</hi> and who had ſerved under three Kings with much Zeal, Fidelity, and Glory, dy'd ſome days ſince: His long life may teach thoſe who are fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the Sea-Air, that one may live as long there as on Land.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:154286:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mounſieur</hi> the <hi>Cavalier D' Arquien</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in reverſion to the Charge of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Colonel of one hundred <hi>Swiſſers</hi> of the <hi>Gardes du Corps</hi> of <hi>Mounſieur:</hi> He is remarkable for his pleaſant Countenance, and handſome Garb; which often ſtretches to Magnificence. He holds one of the firſt degrees among thoſe who are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted handſome men at Court.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>27. <hi>Febr.</hi> 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="letter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:154286:52"/>
               <head>Letter X.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Expect one of my Friends to come and give me an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of an Adventure new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happened, which I deſign to communicate to you: But leſt the Poſt-hour ſhould come too quick upon me, I hope Madam, you will pardon me, if at this time I begin my Letter with the Weeks News.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur de la Mothe Houdancour</hi> died ſome days ſince at the age of fourſcore years, he had ſignaliz'd himſelf at the Siege of <hi>Rochel</hi> and at that of <hi>Montmelian.</hi> The ſeveral Employments and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that he had, were the juſteſt Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of his Deſervings.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:154286:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur de Tholouſe,</hi> Great Almoner to the Queen, and of one of the moſt Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Families of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> and which has produced many Cardinals, after having been Embaſſadour for the King in <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>Poland</hi> (where he deſerved the Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of that Crown for a Cardinals Cap) and after Embaſſadour in <hi>Spain,</hi> and Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the Eſtates in <hi>Languedoc,</hi> where ſerving the King very beneficially, he knew likewiſe how to pleaſe and gain the love of all the Orders, is at length honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Eminent Dignity of Cardinal, and his Holineſs preferred him before ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others upon the Kings Recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who ſtrengthened the Nomination of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will make you no long diſcourſe of the death of <hi>Madam;</hi> you cannot but know it, and fame flies quick with miſadventures that befal Crowned Heads. Yet it may be ſhe may not have told you that that young Princeſs knew the King even in the greateſt diſtraction of her diſtemper, and even then when ſhe knew no other perſon. She was carried to S. <hi>Denis</hi> with all the Pomp due to her Quality, and <hi>Monſieur</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:154286:53"/>the Cardinal of <hi>Bovillon</hi> made an Oration which drew the admiration of all the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly; You know that he joyns to his Great Birth a Capacity above his Age, and a Prudence makes him be look'd on with wonder by all that know him.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ariana</hi> of <hi>Monſieur Corneille</hi> the younger, which has been ſo long expected, appeared on the Stage on Fryday laſt; there was never any thing writ more feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly; and that Princeſs expreſſes her ſelf in Conceptions ſo ſoft and new, that it is not to be imagined any thing can be done better in that way: And to ſay all in a word, the Excellencies of <hi>Bajazet</hi> have not hindred it, Admirers to find ſome in this Piece, and to ſee it more than once.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>March</hi> 5. 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="letter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:154286:54"/>
               <head>Letter XI.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Believe, <hi>Madam,</hi> what I am about to write you of Monſieur <hi>Le</hi>— whom you know very well, and better perhaps than I do, will gain the Credit with you to be thought a pleaſant Adventure; and that the reading it will contribute no leſs to your advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than that of the beſt contrived Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry imaginable which is not ſo true nor ſo new. You know, Madam, that that ſmall Friend of ours, (whom I will now call <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antes</hi>) could never be perſwaded to declare his Choice either of the Church, the Long Robe, or the Sword: for ſometimes he
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:154286:54"/>would by all means be an Abbot; and the next morning, quitting that Reſolution, he would needs be a Counſellour; and within a minute or two after, nothing would ſerve his turn but to be a Souldier. His Relations and Friends having at laſt preſſed him to determine upon ſomething, and having been ſomewhat ſevere upon him for his Irreſolution, he promiſed them he would very ſuddenly declare his Choice, and that on the morrow he would adviſe what courſe was beſt. You will never, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, be able to imagine of whom he took Counſel, and what he did to put himſelf into a Condition to receive it. He bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed a Sute of Arms, and all the Habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of War: He ſent to a Counſellour who was a Friend of his, for a Lawyers Gown, and he intreated an Abbot that was of his Acquaintance to lend him onely for one Afternoon his Surplice and his Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet. All this Harneſs he cauſed to be carried into his Cloſet, where he had four great Looking-glaſſes. In ſhort, being there alone, and having ſhut to the Door, he armes himſelf Cap-a-pe, puts the pot upon his head, takes the Sword and Piſtol
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:154286:55"/>into his hand, conſults his four Looking-glaſſes, ſtruts in a warlike manner half a dozen turns up and down his Cloſet, furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly aſſails the figures in the Tapiſtry, and finds in himſelf Courage, Strength, and Reſolution enough to go to the Army. He therefore examines all the Advantages of that Profeſſion, and the fortunes that he might riſe to: Such and ſuch, ſaid he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf, have had ſuch Commands: Such have been made Marſhals of <hi>France</hi> at ſuch an Age; ſuch have made their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the talk of the World, and their names have ſerved to lengthen out Gazetts, they are gazed at whereever they go, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out with the finger for Brave Men; None dare ſpeak almoſt to them, but their Reputation makes them every where be dreaded. After having run over theſe fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in his brain, he began to make reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the pleaſures he ſhould enjoy upon his Return from a Campaign to appear with all the Equipage of a Marquiſs; for he concluded that gay and fine people made many more conqueſts than others: he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved he ſaw already a great Plume wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in his Hat, and his Coat glittering all
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:154286:55"/>over with Embroydery, that it out-vy'd the Sun, whereever he went; he fancied all Eyes followed him, and he could not doubt but his manly preſence ſupported and ſet off with this Equipage of a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs, and of a Marquiſs that was come from the Army, muſt captive the ſtubborneſt hearts, and make the Ladies fall flat before him. Theſe magnanimous thoughts ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up afreſh his Courage in the Cloſet, and he ſummoned all his Courage together, and redoubled his blows againſt a Squadron of Horſe that was in the Tapiſtry; But, O dire miſchance! blinded with too furious a height of Courage, he unfortunately miſt the Hangings, and his Sword lighting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one of the Looking-glaſſes broke it all in pieces; he preſently throws down his Arms with a reſolution never to handle them more: He believed now he ſhould be unfortunate in the Army, that he ſhould certainly be ſlain, and the broken Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſs was an infallible preſage of it. Well then, Arms laid aſide, he takes up the Gown, and cloaths himſelf like a Counſellour, putting on a little Minikin Ruff, and a ſhort white Perriwig: He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:154286:56"/>with remaining Looking-glaſſes, and thinks this Habit became him mighty pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and begins to feel his Spirits exalted that way: So he ſets himſelf to examine the Advantages of this Profeſſion, which he finds very conſiderable. All People that have Courage, ſaid he within himſelf, do not come to be Marſhals of <hi>France,</hi> the number would then be too great, and one muſt have expoſed ones life a thouſand times before one can juſtly pretend to that Dignity. This thought made him frown and grow pale at once; he found a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours condition much better and ſecurer; and in time, thinks he, I may come to be a Judge, without running any hazard of my Life. He propoſes to himſelf a thouſand Pleaſures and Delights before it came to that; Fancies to himſelf an Anti-chamber, and all the Stairs leading up to it full of Clients ready to caſt themſelves on their Knees before him, and calling him, My Lord. He ſmirks and ſmiles, imagining he ſees among them a great many pretty Women, and theſe thoughts egg on others which fill his whole Brainpan full of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand raviſhing Conceptions. Here there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:154286:56"/>he reſolves to fix his Standard, and to become a Counſellour; but yet he will firſt put on the Rochet to ſee how it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes him. And now he admires his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Gravity, and being mightily taken with himſelf, it comes into his head, that he might one day arrive to be a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal: O then! how ſhould he look in a Scarlet Robe! A Counſellour now ſeems to him but a Coxcomb, in compariſon of a Cardinal: No, no, ſaid he within himſelf, I am not of the humour to undergo the toyls and labour which a man of the Long Robe muſt ſubmit to; what a thouſand troubles doe continually haunt him, after having ſpent a whole evening in reading over Breviates, and perhaps the beſt part of the Night, he muſt be rouzed by four or five a Clock in the morning, with bawling and crying, Good Sir, Remember my cauſe; Pray Sir, Remember my cauſe; and this din continues all the while he is within doors, nor ſcapes he when he gets out, but at every corner ſome are watching to catch him, and ring their cauſe in his ears. If I think to go eat or drink with my Friends, they themſelves grow my Tormentors, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:154286:57"/>are recommending one Cauſe or another; or if I go to court my Miſtreſs, and take an hours divertiſement with her, ſhe is worſe than all the reſt; and being gained by the almighty power of Preſents, I muſt not be admitted to the touch of her finger with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the extracting ſome promiſe from me, and if I promiſe her, I muſt keep my word, and then ten to one fall into injuſtice. No, no, I will not be a Counſellour, 'tis too weighty a Charge; 'tis better being an Abbot, they live as they pleaſe: They— He was about to inlarge himſelf upon the Advantages of this Profeſſion, when a beautiful young perſon whom he loved, and was deſigned to be married too as ſoon as he was ſettled, entred the Cloſet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with her Mother. He believed he had ſhut the door very ſecurely; but alas, he had left the Key in it, his Brain was ſo overwhelmed with Imaginations and Whimſeys concerning the Choice he was to make. He could not be more ſurprized to ſee them come in, than the Ladies were to ſee him in that poſture. They asked him what was the meaning of his being ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited in that manner? He told them he
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:154286:57"/>had determined to become a Church-man, and had put on the Rochet to ſee how the Habit agreed with him: He was hardly to be known, for he had put off his Perruque, his Hair reach'd but to his Ears, and the ſquare Cap he had put on, almoſt covered them, ſo that he look'd mighty ridiculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Ladies in that diſguiſe. They asked him again and again whether he would be ſtedfaſt in his Reſolution to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Church-man? He told them, Yes, and that they could not juſtly complain of him if he took that Courſe; for if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted his Miſtreſs, 'twas for God alone; and that ſince he left her not for any other beauty, they ought not to be angry with him, nor could not accuſe him of Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy. They told him they believed they ſhould be guilty of a great crime, if they ſhould endeavour by any conſiderations to divert him from ſo pious a deſign; and ſoon after left him, without ſeeming either glad or ſorrowful at the accident. The Mother who knew very well, and had ſeen many evidences of his natural Inconſtancy of Mind, was glad to be ſo rid of him. She had another Match ready for her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:154286:58"/>and that fair Maid had ſome inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for him ſhe deſigned her; ſo that things were eaſily concluded. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Abbot heard of it, and was ready to run mad; he comes and throws him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at his Miſtreſſes feet, proteſts, That to enjoy her he would renounce all the Abbeys in the world, and would embrace what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever profeſſion ſhe liked beſt. But it was now too late, and things were too far gone, which did ſo much afflict him, that he is ſince turned Monk. I know not how long his unquiet and irreſolute Spirit will ſuffer him to ſtay in the Convent; but I believe to any one of his humour, confinement will be very tedious and irkſome. Few people know this Adventure, and I am confident, <hi>Madam,</hi> you will find it very extraordinary; and though you may have ſome commiſeration for our friends misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; yet you cannot at the ſame time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear laughing at his follies.</p>
               <p>Never did one year produce ſo many excellent pieces for the Theatre, and the famous <hi>Moliere</hi> has not deceived us in the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:154286:58"/>hopes he inſpired almoſt four years ago, that there ſhould be one day repreſented at the Place Royal a Comical piece after his own Mode, which ſhould be abſolutely accompliſhed. We are excellently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertized ſometimes by thoſe <hi>Pretieuſes</hi> or <hi>Femmes Scavantes</hi> (wiſe women) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by the pleaſant railleries of a certain <hi>Henrietta,</hi> and then by the ridiculous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts of a Fantaſtick, who believes all the world with him, and would perſwade o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſo too; I omit ſpeaking of the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a Father, who would make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that is Maſter of his houſe, and braves it nobly when he is alone; but is as quiet as a Lamb if his Wife but appear. I ſay little likewiſe of the humour of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Triſſotin,</hi> who brimful of underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and puffed up with the glory he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves he has deſerved, appears ſo full of confidence in himſelf, that he looks upon all Mankind beſides as contemptible. The ridiculous opinion which a Mother ſpoil'd with reading, ſeems to have conceived for this <hi>Mounſier Triſſotin</hi> is no leſs pleaſant, and this humour as violent as that of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:154286:59"/>Father in <hi>Tartuffe,</hi> would laſt for ever, if by the ingenious Artifice of the falſe news of a Cauſe loſt, and of a Bankrout (which is an invention not at all inferiour to that of the Buffoon in the impoſtor) a Brother, who though but young, appears a man of exquiſite underſtanding, did not break it off by laying open the whole piece, There is in the third Act a quarrel between <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Triſſotin,</hi> and another wiſe man very divertiſing, and at laſt there is the return of a certain Kitching Maid, called <hi>Martina</hi> who makes the whole Audience laugh with an infinite number of Jolly things, which ſhe ſayes in her Gibbriſh, to prove, That men ſhould have the preference of women. This is a moſt confuſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the moſt conſiderable parts of this Comedy, which has got the vogue of all <hi>Paris.</hi> There are throughout the whole a thouſand wittly quirks, many happy expreſſions, and new and bold ways of ſpeaking, the invention of which can never enough be praiſed, and is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be imitated. Many people have made different applications of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:154286:59"/>in this Comedy, and a quarrel the Author had about eight years ago with a learned man, whom they think repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by <hi>Triſſotin</hi> has given occaſion to the publick talk; but <hi>Monſieur Moliere</hi> is ſufficiently juſtified in that by a ſpeech he made publickly two days before the firſt repreſentation of his piece; nor ought ſuch a pretended Cenſure of this ingenious Comedy give him any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if he be as wiſe, and as able a man, as 'tis ſaid he is; ſince 'twill only make his merit ſhine the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and ſtir up in people a deſire to know him, read his writings, and hear his Sermons. <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed not the reputation of <hi>Socrates,</hi> by playing upon him in his <hi>Faries;</hi> nor was that great Philoſophers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem at all leſſened in <hi>Greece.</hi> But to be the better Judges of the Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy I have been ſpeaking of, I would adviſe all the world to ſee it, and to divertize themſelves, without exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning things at Random, or liſtning to the Critical humour of moſt people,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:154286:60"/>who think it a monſtrous witty thing to find fault.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>March</hi> 12. 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="letter">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:154286:60"/>
               <head>Letter XII.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Arch Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> director of the <hi>French</hi> Academy went with them ſome dayes paſt to <hi>Verſailles</hi> to return the King thanks for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he had done to that Illuſtrious and Learned Society, to take upon himſelf the place of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector in the room of the dead Chancellor. He made his Compliment to the King af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his ordinary rate; that is, with a great deal of Wit and Eloquence. You know well, that with the comlineſs of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which pleaſes at firſt ſight, he has a moſt delightful way of utterance, and that never perſon brought forth words with ſo
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:154286:61"/>much eaſe, aptneſs, and delicacy; beſides he is endowed with all the knowledge of the moſt accompliſhed Doctors, which he gives Evidence off on all occaſions; but I undertake not to write hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Panegerick, leaving it to them deſign his Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mounſieur D'Angeau,</hi> Governour of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jou,</hi> and ſometime Camp-maſter of the Regiment <hi>du Roy,</hi> and deſigned Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor for <hi>Sweden,</hi> who is likewiſe of this Academy, gave a Magnificent treat to this Prelate, with all the Academians of his confraternity, <hi>Mounſieur de Corin</hi> was not of their number, for fear, as 'tis ſaid, leaſt he ſhould lay hold on the occaſion, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to the King of the Comedy 'tis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Mounſieur de Moliere</hi> has made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; but it is not to be believed, that a man, who often converſes with the chief perſons of Court, and whom <hi>Madam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle</hi> honours with the name of Friend, can be the Object of ſo bloody a Satyre. The reſemblance they attribute to him, agrees not with a man, who has publiſhed works with an approbation as general, as that of his paraphraſe on the Song of Songs.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:154286:61"/>I ſpeak not of his works of Gallantry, of which there are many Editions, thoſe are Playes he divertized himſelf with, before he made profeſſion; which ſince his firſt embracing it, he has ever held to the ſame Auſterity he now maintains it with.</p>
               <p>There was in this Aſſembly <hi>Mounſieur Quinault,</hi> ſo well known for his ſmooth and ſoft Verſes; <hi>Mounſieur Deſmareſts</hi> ſo famous for a great number of extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry works, which at once ſet forth both the heighth of Wit, and depth of Knowledge. The Famous <hi>Mounſieur Corneille</hi> the Elder, was here too. I can ſay nothing of him, which will not be beneath him; he is the only man whoſe works may be praiſed without ſeeing them, and from whom notwithſtanding his great Age we may yet expect accompliſhed things, as will doubtleſs, be his laſt Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which will appear next Winter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Pulcheria,</hi> and which cannot fail pleaſing of thoſe, who are in their right Senſes, as it has already plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all have had the happineſs to read
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:154286:62"/>it. There were likewiſe in this Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Company the two <hi>Abbeyes Talle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> the one chief Almoner to <hi>Madam,</hi> whoſe merit is indiſputable, and who with ſo much ſucceſs and, and ſo much benefit to the publick, made that excellent Tranſlation of the Lives of <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch.</hi> The other in a thouſand occaſions has ſhewed his ingenuity, and made himſelf be admired, as well for his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and witty Compoſitions, and by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sermons, which declare his Eloquence and Learning. I had forgot <hi>Mounſieur L'Abbot Jeſtu,</hi> whoſe Sermons char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the whole Court, and whoſe ſoft and Divine Poems give him the preference before all undertake thoſe ways of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, from whom we might expect many admirable things, did not a diſtemper of aſcending vapours hinder his doing any thing. I cannot forget <hi>Mounſieur</hi> the <hi>Duke D'Anguien,</hi> whoſe exquiſite Gallan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, Frolickſome and Gallant Verſes, and high feats of Arms, are unknown to no perſon, who captives all that know him, by an obliging Civility, and by the kindneſſes he is ready to do for all the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:154286:62"/>world upon all occaſions. There are many others very conſiderable for their Worth and Endowments, whoſe names I cannot now remember.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>19. <hi>March.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="letter">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:154286:63"/>
               <head>Letter XIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Now ſend you, <hi>Madam,</hi> what you were pleaſed to let me know was much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired in your Province; and what you have often wiſhed for, to communicate to ſome Gentlemen your Friends: for, for the Ladies, I believe they had rather un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the eſtate of thoſe hearts that ſigh for them, than that of the KING'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Forces.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:154286:63"/>
                  <table>
                     <head>An Account of all the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Foot and Horſe, which are in the Kings Service, according to the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concluded on for their Subſiſtence.</head>
                     <head>Regiments of French Foot, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>53</hi> Men in a Company, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing the Officers.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Regiments Names.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Number of Companies.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Picardy.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Champaigne.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Navarre.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Piedmont.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Normandy.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="102" facs="tcp:154286:64"/>La Marine.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>La Marine.</cell>
                        <cell>32</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Caſtelnau.</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Avergne.</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>De Sault.</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Bandeville.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Regiment du Roy.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Regiment Royal.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Regiment d'Anjou.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Praſlin.</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Lyonnois.</cell>
                        <cell>35</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Dauphin.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Curſol.</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Montaigu.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Turenne.</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>La Motte.</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Dampierre.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Lovigny.</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Grance.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>La Reyne.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <pb n="103" facs="tcp:154286:64"/>Montperat.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Les Vaiſſeaux.</cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Orleans.</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Artois.</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Bretaigne.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Carignan.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Chaſteaneuf.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sourches.</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Vendoſm.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>La Ferte.</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Conty.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>La Fere.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Conde.</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Anguien.</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Jonzai.</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Monperoux.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Bovillon.</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Burgogne.</cell>
                        <cell>33</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>La Marine Noveau.</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Fuſilliers du Roy.</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:154286:65"/>
               <p>In all 46 Regiments, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 1569 Companies of Foot, of 53 men to the Company, amount in all to—83157 men.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Foreign Regiments of Foot.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alſatia,</hi> Twelve Companies, of 182 men, each, make 2184 men.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Engliſh and Scotch,</hi> Twenty Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, of 123 men each, 2460</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rousſillon,</hi> Twenty Companies of the ſame, 2460</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Furſtenburgh,</hi> Twelve Companies, of 182 men each, 2184</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iriſh,</hi> Twelve Companies, of 104 men each, 1248</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Another Iriſh,</hi> Sixteen Companies,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:154286:65"/>of 104 men each: 1664</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Royal Italian,</hi> Twenty ſeven Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, of 104 men each, 2808</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Royal Engliſh,</hi> Eight Companies, of 103 men each, 824</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Stoupe Swiſs,</hi> Twelve Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, 200 men each, 2400</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Erlac Swiſs</hi> the ſame, 2400</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Feſta Swiſs</hi> the ſame, 2400</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Salis Swiſs</hi> the ſame, 2400</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Eight Companies, 103 men each, 824</item>
                  <item>Fifty Unregimented Companies, containing 200 men each, 10000</item>
                  <item>The whole Number of thirteen Forreign Regiments, and fifty Unregimented Companies of divers Nations, amounts unto 36256 men.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:154286:66"/>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Gend'armes</hi> light Horſe, and Muſquetiers on Horſe-back.</head>
                     <item>Four Companies of Guards <hi>du Corps.</hi> 1039 men</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Scotch</hi> Company of <hi>Gend'armes.</hi> 105 men</item>
                     <item>Two Companies of Muſquetiers on Horſe-back, making 554 men</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company of <hi>Gend'armes.</hi> 105 men</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Engliſh</hi> Company of Light-horſe. 110 men</item>
                     <item>The Queens <hi>Gend'armes.</hi> 154</item>
                     <item>The <hi>Dauphins Gend'armes.</hi> 209</item>
                     <item>The <hi>Dauphins</hi> Light-horſe. 108</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gend'armes</hi> d'<hi>Anjou.</hi> 105</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gend'arms d'Orleans.</hi> 154</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Orleans</hi> Light-Horſe. 157</item>
                     <item>Total of the Companies of <hi>Gend'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armes,</hi> Light-horſe, and Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetiers
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:154286:66"/>on Horſe-back above ſpecified. 2800 men.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <head>Light-horſe, of which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments are of ſix Troops, and 54 men each.</head>
                  <item>Colonel General of the ſaid Cavallry</item>
                  <item>Camp-maſter General of the ſaid Cavalry.</item>
                  <item>Commiſſary General of the ſaid Cavalry.</item>
                  <item>Royal du Roy.</item>
                  <item>Two Foreign Regiments.</item>
                  <item>Cravates du Roy.</item>
                  <item>La Regne.</item>
                  <item>Dauphin.</item>
                  <item>Orleans.</item>
                  <item>Conde.</item>
                  <item>Anguien.</item>
                  <item>Rouvray.</item>
                  <item>Gaſſion.</item>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:154286:67"/>
                  <item>Des Forneaux.</item>
                  <item>Joyeuſe.</item>
                  <item>Bonaveze.</item>
                  <item>Fourrilles.</item>
                  <item>Reſnel.</item>
                  <item>Cabonet.</item>
                  <item>Montauban.</item>
                  <item>Pillois.</item>
                  <item>Coulange.</item>
                  <item>Merlin.</item>
                  <item>St. Loupe</item>
                  <item>Cachan.</item>
                  <item>St. Aouſt.</item>
                  <item>Derdelin.</item>
                  <item>Douget.</item>
                  <item>Duconde.</item>
                  <item>Nogent.</item>
                  <item>Tillader.</item>
                  <item>Sourdis.</item>
                  <item>Hiſlez.</item>
                  <item>Bligny.</item>
                  <item>La Fabliere.</item>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:154286:67"/>
                  <item>Lambert.</item>
                  <item>Caberel.</item>
                  <item>Humieres.</item>
                  <item>Proville.</item>
                  <item>Bartillac.</item>
                  <item>Beaupre.</item>
                  <item>Paulmy.</item>
                  <item>Beaufort.</item>
                  <item>Carendo.</item>
                  <item>Sanzay.</item>
                  <item>Chenuet.</item>
                  <item>Novart.</item>
                  <item>Sommieure.</item>
                  <item>Hanjou.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In all 52 Regiments of ſix Troops each, and of 54 men each Troop, make 324 men in a Regiment, in all 16848 men.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:154286:68"/>
               <list>
                  <head>Other Regiments of Horſe, of three Troops each, and fifty four men in a Troop.</head>
                  <item>Coiſlin.</item>
                  <item>Eſtrades.</item>
                  <item>Bethune.</item>
                  <item>Montgeorge</item>
                  <item>Buſenval.</item>
                  <item>Baſleroy.</item>
                  <item>Thrange.</item>
                  <item>Langueville</item>
                  <item>Ragny.</item>
                  <item>Bouillon.</item>
                  <item>Auvergne.</item>
                  <item>Grignan.</item>
                  <item>Laurieres.</item>
                  <item>Granville.</item>
                  <item>Duroures</item>
                  <item>Mere.</item>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:154286:68"/>
                  <item>Thury.</item>
                  <item>Valavoire.</item>
                  <item>Arnolfiny.</item>
                  <item>Harcourt.</item>
                  <item>Armagnac.</item>
                  <item>St. Aignan.</item>
               </list>
               <p>In all 66 Troops of the 22 Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments above, at 54 men to a Troop, amounts to 3564 men.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Foreign Light-horſe.</head>
                  <item>The Prince of <hi>Piemont</hi> Ten Troops, ſome of 64 and others of 54 men. 556</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Koneſmark,</hi> 24 Troops of 54 men each. 1296</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ten Troops, of 54 men. 540</item>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:154286:69"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Schomberg</hi> 3 Troops of 54. 162</item>
                  <item>Roſe 3 Troops the ſame. 162</item>
                  <item>Aouſſet 3 Troops. 162</item>
                  <item>All the above Forreign Cavalry. 3196 men.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Two Regiments of Dragoons.</head>
                  <item>Collonel General of the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons Six Troops, 104 men each. 624</item>
                  <item>Dragoons du Roy, 6 Troops, 54 men each. 324</item>
                  <item>Total of the Dragoons, 948</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Forces belonging to the Kings Houſe.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>French</hi> Regiment of Guards, 30 Companies 100 men each. 3000</item>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:154286:69"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Swiſs</hi> Regiment of Guardes, Ten Companies 200 men each, 2000</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gend'armes du Roy,</hi> 200</item>
                  <item>Light-horſe of the Guard, 200</item>
                  <item>Total 5400 men</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>The Forty ſix Regiments of <hi>French</hi> Foot in this Eſtabliſhment, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to 83697 men.</item>
                  <item>Thirteen Regiments of Foreign Foot amount 36256; to which adding the <hi>Swiſs</hi> Regiments of Guards of 2000 men, and the fifty looſe Companies of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Nations, 41318 men.</item>
                  <item>The Sixteen Companies of <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d'armes,</hi> 2608 men.</item>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:154286:70"/>
                  <item>The Fifty two Regiments of <hi>French</hi> Horſe, 16848 men</item>
                  <item>Twenty two other Regiments of <hi>French</hi> Horſe, 3564 men.</item>
                  <item>Twelve other Regiments of <hi>French</hi> Horſe, 648 men</item>
                  <item>Regiments of Foreign Horſe, 3096</item>
                  <item>Kings <hi>Gend'armes,</hi> 200</item>
                  <item>Kings Light-horſe, 200</item>
                  <item>Total of the Infantry and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry, 155687 men</item>
               </list>
               <p>Since this Eſtabliſhment was ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled, the King in <hi>February</hi> laſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1672. gave Commiſſions fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> raiſing Three Hundred Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panies of Foot, making Fif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teen
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:154286:70"/>thouſand men, to incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate with the old Bodies, and make them 80 Companies each, and ſix ſcore Troops of Horſe to conſiſt of 6000 men, in all  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  21000.</p>
               <p>Which added to 155687,</p>
               <p>Makes 176687 men in all.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>26 <hi>March,</hi> 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="letter">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:154286:71"/>
               <head>Letter XIV.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have nothing of News <hi>Madam,</hi> to communicate this Week, unleſs it be the Kings Journey to <hi>Verſailles.</hi> I know you have ſeen that place, and that you have read the excellent deſcription given of it by <hi>Madamoiſelle de Scudery;</hi> but the <hi>Verſailles</hi> you have ſeen, and that which ſhe has writ of are much different from that which now is; and the King never is a Month a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:154286:71"/>from thence, but he finds ſomething new, and the place appears changed, by reaſon of the beauties inceſſantly added. The <hi>Grotto</hi> has been lately imbeliſhed with many incomparable Figures, they have placed there a great Sun; with a many Nymphs abour him, Crowning him, and waſhing his feet and his hands. This wonderful piece (the largeſt yet there) is the Workmanſhip of <hi>Meſsieurs Gerardon,</hi> and <hi>Renaudin:</hi> In two niches which are of the ſide of it, are placed four Horſes of the Sun, which ſeem to breath forth fire, and look as if they were taking their Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riere, but are ſtop'd by the powerful <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> that withhold them. <hi>Monſieur Guerin</hi> made one halfe of this work, and <hi>Meſsieurs Gaſpard,</hi> and <hi>Baltazard</hi> the other. There are likewiſe placed in this <hi>Grotto</hi> many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther curious Figures of <hi>Monſieur Battiſta</hi> a very famous Artiſt, from whence it appears, that <hi>France</hi> do's produce men great in theſe works, as well as <hi>Italy.</hi> I ſhould never have done, ſhould I ſpeak of all the wonders the Waters produce in that delicious Paradice. The <hi>Sieur Denys</hi> brings
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:154286:72"/>it thither by wonderful Pumps and Aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts, and <hi>Monſieur Faucine</hi> do's with it things ſurpaſſing imagination, Witneſs the Mariſh, the Tree, and the Mount of Water, not to forget the Theatre, where the changes of the Scenes of Water are as quick and faſt as in the other, where the Machines are the thickeſt; but one would think there ſhould want water for all theſe things, and ſo there muſt, but for the great care of thoſe that bring it to that place; for there are are very large Terraſſes excellently Wrought and Imbeliſhed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which are Ciſterns of Water. The Miracles done by <hi>Monſieur Nautre</hi> in theſe Magnificent Gardens are no leſs admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The great quantities of Orange-trees Planted in the ground, may be a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of it, as well as thoſe great Trees tranſplanted to inlarge the great Walk, a thing never before ſeen. There are yet a thouſand things might be ſaid of this Caſtle, which ſurpaſſes the Palace of <hi>Armida.</hi> I might ſpeak of the Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and thoſe who are the Architects; but that would be too long a Story, and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:154286:72"/>therefore had better put it off to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, or rather till they be finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>April</hi> 2. 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="letter">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:154286:73"/>
               <head>Letter XV.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know not, <hi>Madam,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the News I have ſent you ſince the Month of <hi>January</hi> hath ſatisfied your Curioſity. I am of the opinion, that what I have hitherto done, has only ſhewed my obedience in punctually writing you; but I hope in time to ſend you more pleaſing and plentifull news.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur</hi> the <hi>Cardinal de Bonzy</hi> received this week the Cap from the Kings hands, in the preſence of the Cardinals <hi>de Retz, Bovillon,</hi> and <hi>Maldoching.</hi> I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy writ you ſomething of <hi>Cardinal Bovillon,</hi> and you are not ignorant of the great merit
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:154286:73"/>of Cardinal <hi>de Retz,</hi> and that both his wit and his misfortunes have made him equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly famous as well as his fidelity to his Friends; and you know likewiſe, that his Juſtice and Generoſity, of which every one is a partaker, who comes within the reach of his kindneſs, make him no leſs admired. All men ſeem'd aſtoniſhed to ſee at this Ceremony <hi>Monſieur Priam,</hi> formerly Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident at <hi>Mantoua,</hi> who had ſeen the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Cardinal of <hi>Bonzy,</hi> great Uncle to this man, and Grand Almoner to <hi>Mary de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis,</hi> receive the Cap from the hands of <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth.</p>
               <p>The Duke <hi>de Chaune,</hi> famous for his Embaſſis to <hi>Rome,</hi> as likewiſe for the good ſervice he has done the King in the States of <hi>Brittain,</hi> of which he is Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; ſome days ſince preſented the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duties of that Province to his Majeſty.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Bethane,</hi> ſo well known under the Title of <hi>Count de Charoſt,</hi> whoſe ſervices, fidelity and acknowledgements to his Benefactors makes as eſteemable as his Illuſtrious birth, which he derives from
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:154286:74"/>the ancient <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Bethune</hi> has taken his Oath between the Kings hands for the charge of Lieutenant General of <hi>Picardy,</hi> in Exchange of that of Captain of the Guard <hi>du Corps,</hi> which is given to the Duke <hi>de Duras.</hi> You know Madam this Duke is one of the moſt ancient Houſes in <hi>France</hi> that has a vaſt wit, that he has in all Armies where he has ſerved, given approved marks of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Conduct, and gain'd the eſteem of a very great Captain.</p>
               <p>You may have heard e're this of the Death of the Dutcheſs <hi>Dowager</hi> of <hi>Orleans,</hi> her Age, her Family, and her Chriſtian Virtues are all ſo well known to you, that I need not enlarge my ſelf on that point.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>April</hi> 9. 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="letter">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:154286:74"/>
               <head>Letter XVI.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince 'tis your deſire, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, after having heard ſomething concerning the <hi>French</hi> Academy, that I ſhould likewiſe write you ſomething concerning that of the Abbot of <hi>Aubignac,</hi> of which, as you ſay, you have only heard ſome confuſed ſpeeches. I will tell you, that it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>l' Academie des belles Lettres,</hi> and that its inſtitution was for examining works of Eloquence and Poeſy. The firſt day of every Month a diſcourſe was held of the ſeveral Conditions of man, in which Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence was held neceſſary. The holding the firſt diſcourſe fell to <hi>Monſieur Blondeau,</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:154286:75"/>Advocate in Parliament, he held it on the Eloquence of the Bar, and acquitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf very well in the great Hall of the <hi>Hoſtel de Matignon,</hi> before an Aſſembly compoſed of many perſons of quality, both of the one and the other Sex. <hi>Monſieur the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis de Villaines</hi> gain'd applauſe the Month following on Military Eloquence. The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion this diſcourſe made is a ſign of its Excellence; and therefore I'll ſay no more, but paſs to the third, which fell upon <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Abbot of <hi>St. Germain.</hi> The two former having made diſcourſe; with regard to their profeſſion, this illuſtrious Abbot would make his on the Eloquence of the Pulpit, and had great ſucceſs in it, to the wonderful ſatisfaction of the whole Aſſembly. <hi>Monſieur Perachon</hi> gain'd cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit the Month following, and the other Academians addicted themſelves from Month to Month to give Evidences of their Wit and Learning. At the end of theſe Diſcourſes they read ſome works of Poeſy. compoſed by ſome of the Gentlemen of the Academy, and theſe are the names of the Compoſers.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:154286:75"/>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Abbot of <hi>Aubignac,</hi> director</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur de Vaumorieres</hi> Subdirector.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur Gueret</hi> Secretary of the Academy</item>
                  <item>The late Marquis <hi>de Chatelet.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Marquis <hi>de Villaines.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Marquis <hi>d' Arbaux.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur Petit,</hi> Director after the Abbot <hi>d' Aubignac.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur Perachon</hi> Advocate in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur</hi> The Abbot of <hi>Vilars.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Abbot of <hi>Villeſerain,</hi> at preſent Biſhop of <hi>Senes,</hi> Director after <hi>Monſieur Petit.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The late Abbot of <hi>Ganaret.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur de La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nay,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur Care</hi> Advocate in Parliament.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur Richelet.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur de Perier.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The late <hi>Monſieur de Baurin</hi> Advocate in the Counſel.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur Barallis</hi> Phyſitian.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Abbot of St. <hi>Germain.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The illuſtrious Academy has been broke off ſince the Abbot of <hi>Villeſerain</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Senes,</hi> there was a deſign ſometime before to bring women in,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:154286:76"/>and <hi>Madam de Villedieu</hi> was propoſed, whoſe works were grown ſo famous; they talked likewiſe of Madam the Marchioneſſe of <hi>Guiberminy,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Villaines,</hi> who has a piercing and delicate wit, and cannot be too much prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; nor did they forget Madam the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſſe <hi>Deſhoulieres,</hi> you muſt needs have heard ſpeak of her (Madam) for his worth is every where known, ſhe writes very Politely both in Verſe and Proſe. There run up and down ſome Gallant pieces of her Dog called <hi>Gas,</hi> who is lately turned excellent Poet, ſo that his works deſerve to be Printed. This Lady has made him the <hi>Cerberus</hi> of <hi>Pornaſſus,</hi> to defend its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance againſt Dablers. I have incloſed a Coppy of his Verſes being a Letter to the Count <hi>L. T.</hi> that you may judge of his wit, and when you have read them, I believe you will ſay, you never ſaw more natural Verſes, nor heard of a more Ingenious Cur; but the reaſon is evident, all Spanels have not ſuch witty Miſtreſſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur de Moranges,</hi> Director of the Finances died laſt week, he was an honeſt
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:154286:76"/>and an ingenious man, and the Gazetſayes ſo much of him, that I can ſay nothing comes near it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Barron of <hi>Schonborn,</hi> Nephew and Envoy extraordinary of the Elector of <hi>Mentz</hi> had Audience from the King, he demonſtrated under the face of Youth, a Prudence ſurprizes the Aged, and buſineſs ſeems ſo natural to him, that the moſt knotty things are eaſie, this he has given ſuch evidences of, and I have been aſſured it by ſo many perſons that know him well, that you may believe all I write of this young Miniſter is true.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur</hi> the <hi>Count de Molina,</hi> extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Ambaſſador from <hi>Spain,</hi> made his Entry accompanied with Marſhal <hi>de Grance,</hi> and ſome dayes after was condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to have Audience from the King, by <hi>Monſieur</hi> the Count <hi>de Armagnac.</hi> You may obſerve one thing, which thoſe who have read the Gazets this twenty years, have not perhaps taken notice of, which is, that the Ambaſſadors of Crowned heads, or thoſe that are treated, as ſuch
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:154286:77"/>are always conducted to their Audience by a Prince of the Blood, and that he, who receives them on the day of their publick Entrance, never conducts them to the <hi>Louvre.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>April</hi> 16. 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="letter">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:154286:77"/>
               <head>Letter XVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Promiſed you Madam to ſend you all the new Modes; and yet I have not, you tell me, writ you one word of them in any of my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. The Courts being ſo long in mourning has been the cauſe of it. It has put a ſtop to the inventions of many and ſmothered thoſe have come forth in their Infancy; yet I will tell you, That they wear their Gowns ſo long Waſted, that it reaches almoſt to their Thighs, who have but little Haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
               <p>The men ſtill wear their Hats ſo large, that the old men (who for fear of appearing
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:154286:78"/>ridiculous; wore great ones while others wear little ones) appear at preſent what they ſought to avoid, becauſe they will not change their Mode; and the great Hats of that time, are the little ones of this.</p>
               <p>They wear now few Hatbands of Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon or Silk, and Gold Hatbands are come again in Mode. I know not whether it will long be ſuffered; but within this eight dayes they begin to wear all their Coats Laced or Embroidred with Gold and Silver. 'Tis ſeldom but the ſame thing has happened over again; but time paſt is now no more, and <hi>Monſieur de la Reynie</hi> attempts nothing he brings not to paſs; he has done things ſince he has been Lieutenant of the Policy, that were thought impoſſible, and which many ages attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in vain; no Judge can be more equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, uncorrupr or zealous in the ſervice of his King. The populacy are ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to him, they ought to contrive a way to Eternize his memory.</p>
               <p>After having ſpoken of the Modes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the habits of Men and Women,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:154286:78"/>I muſt now entertain you with one newer then any of thoſe I have ſpoken of, and which relates to Houſhold-ſtuff. I was lately at a Gentlewomans, who is none of the higheſt quality; but whoſe Gallant is extreamly rich; they told me they would ſhew me a Hall, very neatly furniſhed, and they carried me into a Room, whoſe Hangings were of fine Damask. Whilſt they made me look out at a Window had its proſpect on a very fine Garden, that Hanging was gone in an inſtant, ſo that but turning about, I ſaw the Rooms hung with Hangings of another Colour, and the firſt drawn up like a Corniſh about it. Admiring this invention, they bid me pull a little weight that was hid in the Corner of the Room, where it was not ſeen, and yet was faſtened to Strings of Silk and Gold, which I had no ſooner as it were touched, but the ſecond Hanging came up, and diſpoſed it ſelf into little folds, making Buttons as it were between the Corniſh, and diſcovered a rich Green Hanging, adorned with many Pictures with curious Frames. Never was any thing ſo pleaſant to me, and I cannot but admire at thoſe that found
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:154286:79"/>out this pretty invention, and had I gone out of the Hall as often as it changed, I could never have believed it to be the ſame Room. The Inventors of this, they ſay, are framing a Bed ſhall change as often. I thought I could never have ſent you ſo much of new Modes; but I ſee this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle will always furniſh me with matter.</p>
               <p>One of <hi>Monſieur</hi> the <hi>primier Preſidents</hi> Sons, has lately married a Daughter of <hi>Monſieur de Calucet,</hi> Governour of the Caſtle of <hi>Nantes.</hi> I will inform you as ſoon as I can of the particular endowments of theſe young married people.</p>
               <p>The King has nominated <hi>Monſieur D' Aquin</hi> his principal Phyſitian. I will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeak of his worth nor capacity, the Kings choice is enough to make both known.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur de la Chambre</hi> is nominated principal Phyſitian to the Queen; he is much eſteemed in Court, and has the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of an able man.</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:154286:79"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur Renadot,</hi> whoſe long Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the infinite number of diſtemper'd perſons he has had for many years to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice upon, ſhould be one of the ableſt Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians in <hi>Paris,</hi> is by the King choſen Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Phyſitian to the <hi>Dauphin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Since <hi>January</hi> laſt has been continued the publiſhing of <hi>le Journal des Scavans,</hi> which you have ſometimes read with delight, 'tis a good and a profitable Work, the Author is in much eſteem, and has the Honour to be favoured by a great Miniſter of State.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>April</hi> 23. 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="letter">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:154286:80"/>
               <head>Letter XVIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Now ſend you a Liſt of the General Officers nominated by the King to ſerve him this Campaigne. I will not be ſo poſitive as to affirm it ſo exact, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing may be forgot, nor nothing altered, or that the degrees are infallibly obſerved; but in ſhort, 'tis the beſt I could get, and I give you part in it. I believe there's many people in your Countrey don't know halfe ſo much.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Names of the General Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Kings Army.</head>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <pb n="135" facs="tcp:154286:80"/>
                        <item>MONSIEUR, <hi>Generalliſſimo.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monnſieur <hi>de Turenne,</hi> General.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Lieutenant Generals.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Gadagne.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur the Duke <hi>de Feuillade.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur the Count <hi>de Soiſſons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur the grand maſter of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery.</item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Lorge.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Rochfort.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <pb n="136" facs="tcp:154286:81"/>
                        <head>Marſhals de Camp.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur the Chevalier <hi>de Lorrain.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>Martinet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Montal.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Fourille</hi> is Camp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter of the Cavalry, and Serves always.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Brigadiers of Horſe.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de M.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de C.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Feuille.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>le Comte du Roy.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Chazeron.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Brigadiers of Foot.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Beauveau.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Adjutants of the Camp.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur the Count <hi>d' Ayen.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="137" facs="tcp:154286:81"/>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>D' Albret.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur the Chevalier <hi>de Nogent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur the Marquis <hi>d' Angeau.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Breaute.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de la Roche Courton.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Officers of the Army of Monſieur the Prince.</head>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Lieutenant Generals.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur the Count <hi>d' Guiche.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de St. Avre.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>Faucaut.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Marſhals of the Camp.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur the Count <hi>du Pleſſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur the Count <hi>de Nogent.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="138" facs="tcp:154286:82"/>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Magaloty.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Chiſeuile.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Commiſſary General of the Horſe.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de la Cardoniere.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Brigadiers of Horſe.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Beauveze.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>Vivien.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Fourneaux.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Brigadiers of Foot.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>Pilloy.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:154286:82"/>Officers of the Army to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Monſieur the Marſhal <hi>de Crequy.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Lieutenant General.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Nanere.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Marſhals of the Camp.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Vaubrun.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur the Cavalier <hi>du Pleſſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Brigadiers of Horſe.</head>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>M.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Monſieur <hi>de Pierrefite.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The King has nominated <hi>Monſieur de Sainſandoux,</hi> Major of the Regiment of Guards, Major General of his Army; he has likewiſe nominated <hi>Monſieur Tracy,</hi> Captain of the Guards, Major General to the Prince, and <hi>Monſieur de la Marrilliere,</hi> Lieutenant Collonel of the Queens Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Major general of the third Army,</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:154286:83"/>
                  <head>General Officers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Allies.</head>
                  <item>Monſieur de <hi>Luxembourg,</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant General to the Biſhop of <hi>Munster.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Monſieur <hi>de Chamilly,</hi> Lieutenant General to the Biſhop of <hi>Cullen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Monſieur <hi>de Renel</hi> to command the Horſe.</item>
                  <item>Monſieur de <hi>Mornas</hi> to command the Foot.</item>
                  <item>Monſieur <hi>de Beaudevis</hi> to command The Army of <hi>Roſſillon</hi> to be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Monſieur <hi>le Bret.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>I fancy, that after this account of the Land-Armies, you may likewiſe be deſirous to know the force by Sea, and that theſe-veral names of the Ships may divertize,</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:154286:83"/>
                  <head>A LIST of the ſeveral Ships of the Fleet, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Service this year 1672.</head>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>
                           <hi>At Rochefort.</hi> Names of the Captains and Ships.</head>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Rabinieres.</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Superbe,</hi> 1300 Tuns, 70 Guns.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Gabaret.</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>LeFoudrogant,</hi> 1300 Tuns, 68 Guns</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Gombaut.</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Grand,</hi> 1100 Tuns, 64 Guns.</item>
                        <pb n="142" facs="tcp:154286:84"/>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Michaut.</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>LeConquerant,</hi> 1100 Tuns, 64 Guns</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Grancay.</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>L' Illuſtre,</hi> 1100 Tuns, 70 Guns.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Beaulieu.</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>L' Admirable,</hi> 1100 Tuns, 70 Guns</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſ. <hi>Le Comandeur de Verdille,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>L' Invincible,</hi> 1100 Tuns, 70 Guns</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Deſtivall,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Sans-pareil,</hi> 1100 Tuns, 62 Guns</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur D'Ymagnion,</label>
                           <hi>L' Excellent,</hi> 1000 Tuns, 56 Guns</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur de Blenac,</label>
                           <hi>Le Fort,</hi> 1000 Tuns, 54 Guns.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur de Tourville,</label>
                           <hi>Le Gallant,</hi> 700 Tuns, 44 Guns.</item>
                        <pb n="143" facs="tcp:154286:84"/>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Villeneuf Ferier,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Brillant,</hi> 600 Tuns, 40 Guns.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de la Vigery,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Hazardeux,</hi> 550 Tuns, 34 Guns</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>Fire-Ships.</head>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Rocachon.</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Fin.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Ozcer Thomas,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Perilleux.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Vidaut,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Voile.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>du Rivault,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>L' Inconnu.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Serpaut,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>De Deguiſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="144" facs="tcp:154286:85"/>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Chaboſſeau.</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>L' Entreprenant.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>At Breſt.</head>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Le Comte d' Eſtrees,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>L' St. Philip</hi> Admiral.</item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Queſne,</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant General.</label>
                           <hi>Le Terrible.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>des Ardans,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Tonnant.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Vallebelle,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Brave.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Suerdis,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Valliant.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Larcou,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Temeraire.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb n="145" facs="tcp:154286:85"/>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Quyovet,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>L' Oriflame.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Queruville,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Bourbon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>d' Infreville,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Rubes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Desbeville,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Duc.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Coquelin,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Lacolle.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>Panetier,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>L' Heureux.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Bleor,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>L' Alcion.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>La Rocque Souftreet,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>Le Hardy.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <pb n="146" facs="tcp:154286:86"/>
                        <head>Light Frigats.</head>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur—</label>
                           <hi>La Tempeſt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Bellemont,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>L' Aurora.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur <hi>de Gravencon,</hi>
                           </label>
                           <hi>La Railleuſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur de St. Michel,</label>
                           <hi>La Subtile.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur de Grosbois,</label>
                           <hi>La Lutine.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <label>Monſieur Delmonts,</label>
                           <hi>La Galliarde.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="147" facs="tcp:154286:86"/>
                     <list>
                        <head>Brulots.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Le Trompeur.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Le Serpent.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>
                           <hi>Foiſts.</hi> Two Tartans.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Monſieur du Queſne</hi> is to Guard the Coaſt of <hi>Rochel</hi> with a Squadron of fourteen Ships.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Monſieur Martel</hi> to Command a Squadron of fourteen Ships for a Reſerve.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>23 <hi>April</hi> 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="letter">
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:154286:87"/>
               <head>Letter XIX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adam,</hi> I now ſend you a part of the New Books are lately publiſhed by <hi>Monſieur Barbin. The Beralde,</hi> of an unknown Author, you will find well writ. The Exiles of <hi>Madam de Velledieu,</hi> will divertize you extreamly; the Contrivances are well laid, and delicately handled; and that witty La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, all whoſe Writings have yet gain'd ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, will deſerve renewed Praiſes. I ſend you likewiſe the Second Tome of the Works of <hi>Monſieur le Paiis.</hi> The former had great ſucceſs, be you Judge of this. I will ſend to you within this eight days a new Book of <hi>Monſieur Menage;</hi> they are
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:154286:87"/>farther Obſervations on the <hi>French Tongue</hi> Though a work is not always to be valued by its ſucceſs, yet may we judge of the worth of this by the general repute it has gained, ſince it is with Juſtice it pleaſes; and I doubt not but in a little time in ſtead of ſaying, <hi>Parler Vaugelas,</hi> (ſpeak, <hi>Vauge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi>) to praiſe thoſe that ſpeak well, we ſhall ſay, <hi>Parler Menage.</hi> This great man (for ſo we may call him for his abundance of Learning) expoſes now all the different manners of ſpeaking which ſignifie, or which we would have ſignifie the ſame thing; he quotes all thoſe have made uſe of them, and after having given their true derivation, determines for the moſt part in favour of Cuſtom, which he ſays is the Soveraign Maſter of Language, which we ſhould moſt apply our ſelves to, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing which, though we break the Rules, we yet ſpeak well. This deciſion of ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous an Author, will be very profitable, and will in the future bring all the world to underſtand and ſpeak things in the ſame way, the contrary of which has been pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed hitherto: for ſome knowing men have ſpoke according to Cuſtom, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:154286:88"/>according to fancy, that is, ſometimes one way, ſometimes another, which in time has much obſcured the Language. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Madam,</hi> all <hi>France</hi> is much obliged to <hi>Monſieur Menage</hi> for the pains he has taken to teach them to ſpeak. Do but obſerve the Authors he quotes: Monſieur <hi>Vauge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi> whom he often approves, and often condemns; Meſſieurs <hi>Balzack, Malherbe, Sarazin, Vecture, Mamard, St. Amant, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beuf, Ablancourt, Colletet, Gombaut,</hi> the Father <hi>Rapin, Racon, Mairet,</hi> the Father <hi>Chiflet, Deſmareſts, Gomberville,</hi> the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot <hi>Chaſteliu,</hi> the Abbot <hi>Saſsy, Mereray, Sorel, Charpentier, Briauville,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Vauce, Pelliſon la Mothe, le Vayer,</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Bohours, Patru, Chapelain, Segrais, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolles, Benſerade, Corneille, Dandilly,</hi> the Author of the <hi>Count du Gabalis, Bary, La Fountaine, Talleucant, Meſsieurs du Port Royal,</hi> and <hi>Madamoiſelle de Scudery.</hi> I have not obſerved the degrees of theſe Great Wits, 'twould be too bold an Enterprize: Monſieur <hi>Menage</hi> has not obſerved them, not having quoted them, but as he had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of their Works to authorize his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. He has ſpoken of ſome a dozen
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:154286:88"/>others, but their Worth being grown old, I thought it not neceſſary to enlarge my Letter with their Names.</p>
               <p>The King has given the Seals to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>D' Aligre:</hi> I have told you his Worth already, and his ſundry Employs and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſies: His Majeſty, at making him this Great Preſent, ſpoke much in his praiſe; letting, by what he ſaid, all the World know the Confidence he had in him. It is to be obſerved that a Chancellours Son was never before made Keeper of the Seal.</p>
               <p>All <hi>Paris</hi> are running every day to the Fathers of the Oratory, to ſee the Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoleum of the Late Chancellour, erected by the Contrivance of Monſieur <hi>de Brun,</hi> When I have ſeen it, I will tell you more, both of the Work and the Contriver.</p>
               <p>The Phyſicians in a Body, and in their Doctors Habit, and having the Sieur <hi>Puy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> their Director in the head of them, have been at St. <hi>Germains</hi> to complement the Three Principal Phyſitians to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties. What a brave thing it is to have theſe Employments which bring Honour, and ſomething elſe.</p>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:154286:89"/>
               <p>The Equipages of the King, <hi>Monsieur,</hi> the Princes and Officers of the Army, are gone hence this Week. Never was any thing ſeen ſo great, and for eight days all the Windows were filled with People, as at a Publick Entrance. Among this great number of Mules, Horſes and Chariots richly covered, were to be ſeen fourſcore Waggons, whoſe coverings were not ſo rich and gaudy as thoſe of the Chariots, but they were better lined, and the Horſes could hardly draw them. They were loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, as 'tis ſaid, with what we call the Nerves and Sinews of War, and guarded with the Kings <hi>Gend'arms</hi> and Light-horſe. The Covetous looked with greedy eyes on this great maſs of Money: Mothers wiſh'd it for portions for their Daughters, Lovers to make Preſents to their Miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Debtors to pay their Debts; In ſhort, every one wiſhed to ſupply his occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and the leaſt intereſſed had their thoughts too. That which was moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in it, was, that every one believed what he wiſhed for would not much leſſen the ſum, nor do the King or his Armies any wrong; and yet had this Money been to be
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:154286:89"/>diſtributed according to every ones wiſh, there muſt many yet have remained unſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and not a denier of it gone out of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Equipages during the laſt week have filled all the ſtreets of <hi>Paris,</hi> the old Caſtle of St. <hi>Germain</hi> has been as full of thoſe who went to take their leaves of the King. The Ambaſſador of <hi>England</hi> has taken it for a long time, being to return to the King his Maſter; he is of the Houſe of the <hi>Montagues,</hi> which is no leſs Honourable in <hi>England,</hi> then well known in <hi>France.</hi> He is a man of excellent Parts, of which the particular reſpect he has ever ſhewn here to men of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, is a ſufficient Witneſs. He leaves them very melancholly for his departure, and ſome Ladies of very great reputation are ſharers in their ſorrow, with whom he uſed to ſpend the time he could ſpare from the ſerious buſineſs of his Imploy; he preſented to the King the <hi>Sieur de Godol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin,</hi> who is to ſtay with his Majeſty during this Campaigne. The Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of <hi>Savoy,</hi> the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Reſident, and the extraordinary Envoys of <hi>Mentz</hi> and <hi>Genoua,</hi> took likewiſe leave of his Majeſty, and ſo
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:154286:90"/>did all the Sovereign Courts, and the Provoſt of the Merchants. All the Biſhops that are here, were there likewiſe, and all perſons of any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion imitated them. Theſe marks of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and love to the greateſt of Kings had never ended, if his Majeſties Warlike ardour had not made him leave St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main</hi> ſooner then he intended. He is gone with a ſmall Train; but he is gone to find an Army ſo great, and numerous, that never any of his Predeceſſors ſaw the like. His Majeſty hath left the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Affairs to the Queen, with a Counſel compoſed of the Keeper of the Seal <hi>Villeroy le Tellier</hi> and <hi>Colbert.</hi> Their merit is ſo well known, that I can ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to their advantage, which will not be infinitely below it, or which has not been ten thouſand times ſaid.</p>
               <p>I ſhould in my Letter concerning the new Modes have told you of ſome words, which though they be not new, yet are at preſent <hi>a la mode. Par toute Terre</hi> (thorough the whole World) is one of them, and when they would ſpeak highly of any thing that it is approved or pleaſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:154286:90"/>They will ſay they talk of that <hi>Par toute Terre,</hi> That is liked <hi>Par toute Terre,</hi> That is approved <hi>Par toute Terre.</hi> The Gallants now ſcarce ſpeak fifty words without uſing that ten times, as well as the word <hi>Violant,</hi> which is much worſe applied to all they uſe it for, to ſay, That is troubleſome, they will ſay, <hi>Cela eſt violant;</hi> to expreſs he has wrong, they ſay the ſame, and ſeem to affect to make it ſerve to expreſs things with which it has not the leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement. I believe, <hi>Madam,</hi> you never heard of the like Foppery; thoſe who have hitherto invented new words or expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, have ſtudied to make the beſt they could ſignifie what they would ſay. The Verb <hi>Deſoler</hi> is no leſs <hi>a la mode;</hi> and now when any one would ſay, That another is trubleſome ſhe ſayes, <hi>Qu'elle la deſole;</hi> when they would ſay, One is melancholly, they ſay, <hi>Qu'on eſt deſole;</hi> and in ſhort, they apply this word to any thing has any pain or trouble in it.</p>
               <p>I cannot reſolve to cloſe this Letter, till I give you a Story I have juſt now learned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Megius</hi> a learned man, and known by many fine works, was lately at a Ladies, his
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:154286:91"/>friends accompanied with <hi>Bretius</hi> a young man of great wit, but who was not very forward in ſhewing it, having been there a good while, and ſaid nothing. This Lady (<hi>Megius</hi> his friend) was an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of Aſtrology, and believed ſhe knew ſomething of it, which was enough to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a diſcourſe of it. That brought on o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and at laſt they talked of fixing of <hi>Mercury; Megius</hi> ſaid, That if they would ſend for ſome, he would fix it; ſome was preſently brought, and he did what he had promiſed, to the Ladies great amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and more to an Aſtrologers, her friend, that was with her. This preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Aſtrologer asked him how he came to know what he had done, if he had learnt it by reading, if any one had ſhewed it him; or if by ſome chance he had hit of it, or by Art had found out the ſecret. By one of theſe wayes indeed, anſwered <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> I learnt what you have now ſeen me do; for look you there, ſaid he, turning to <hi>Bretius,</hi> who had yet ſpoke only Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſyllables, is he that taught me what I have now done; both the Lady and her friend preſently caſt their Eyes upon him,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:154286:91"/>they viewed him from head to foot, and blamed themſelves in private, that his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence had made him paſs with them for a man of no Senſe. They offered him now a thouſand praiſes, and ſpoke of him with admiration: In the remainder of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, he made them perceive he had his ſhare of wit; but inſtead of ſatisfying their curioſity in what they deſired, he only told them things that inflamed them the more, and made them paſſionately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to unite a firm friendſhip with him. night coming on, obliged them to part ſooner then they would have done, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one had his deſign, as you will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the ſequel of the ſtory.</p>
               <p>The Aſtrologer, whom I ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after call <hi>Zoroaſtes,</hi> came to ſee <hi>Bretius</hi> the next morning, and expreſſed ſuch a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſire to learn his ſecret, that the young man, who had long wiſhed for ſome body to make a Fop of, was mighty glad to have found one. <hi>Zoroaſtes</hi> on his part pretermited nothing might engage his friendſhip; preſented him, gave him great treats, and all yet to no purpoſe; for the young man, who had reſolved to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:154286:92"/>ſport, and was mightily pleaſed with theſe treats, had the cunning to delay him ſo long, till himſelf was almoſt weary of it. At length the day broke, which was to enlighten <hi>Zoroaſtes</hi> Knowledge, and all things being prepared, <hi>Bretius</hi> weighs a little Ball of Wax which he had brought with him, and which weighed almoſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and put it into the  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  and told <hi>Zoroaſtes</hi> after having covered it, that it muſt ſtand two hours without being looked on, and that in the mean time he might go to his Cloſet, and caſt a Figure to ſee if the work ſhould have good effect. The two hours being run out, they found there very good Silver, at leaſt it appeared ſo to the eyes of <hi>Zoroaſtes,</hi> who went preſently to ſhew it three or four Gld-ſmiths, who affirmed it as good as any they had in their Shops. His Careſſes now to <hi>Bretius</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deſcribed; he almoſt ſmothered him with kindneſs, and treated him like a man who was able to teach him a ſecret, by which he hoped to become maſter of more treaſure then all the Kings of <hi>Europe;</hi> ſwel'd with theſe hopes, he conjured him to give him where withall only to make
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:154286:92"/>Silver. <hi>Bretius</hi> gave him one of his Balls, but it melted, and came to nothing with our Aſtrologer. Hecomplains to <hi>Bretius</hi> of it, who told him his curioſity was the cauſe, which had made him too ſoon remove the Cover, he did it over again with him, and it ſucceeded as before. <hi>Zoroaſtes</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, and one day tells the Prince of it, then again tell <hi>Bretius</hi> what he had ſaid of him: The young man was in a Peck of Troubles, and was forced to acknowledge it was but a trick of Legerdemain, and to ſhew him his cunning, and ſo things ſtopt there. There are many people ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be cheated by ſuch fine outward appearances. Me thinks, <hi>Madam,</hi> this Letter is ſomewhat long; I know not whether it may divertize you, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any of the former have pleaſed you: But I know I will uſe my endeavour to find out things ſo pleaſant and delightful, that if it be poſſible you ſhall be ſatisfied.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>May</hi> 1. 1672.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:154286:93"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:154286:93"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:154286:94"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:154286:94"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
